<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Delightful history of the life &amp; death of that renowned &amp; famous St. Patrick, champion of Ireland containing his heroick actions, and valorous atchievments in Europe, Asia, and Affrick : with other remarkable passages, from his cradle to his grave.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12320766</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12320766</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 936:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Delightful history of the life &amp; death of that renowned &amp; famous St. Patrick, champion of Ireland containing his heroick actions, and valorous atchievments in Europe, Asia, and Affrick : with other remarkable passages, from his cradle to his grave.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 152 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Patrick, --  Saint, 373?-463?</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  To 1172.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:1"/>
            <p>The Delightful HISTORY OF THE Life &amp; Death OF That Renowned &amp; Famous <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> Champion of <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing His Heroick Actions, and Valorous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievments in <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With other Remarkable Paſſages, from his Cradle to his Grave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings Armes</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath been in all Ages ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted neceſſary to preſerve Antient Monuments from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contaminated or obliterated; &amp; the more precious the Monuments were, the more care &amp; induſtry hath been uſed for their Preſervations: The moſt Ignorant among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were not negligent in this matter; but as for the more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Heathens, ſuch was their care, and ſo great their Charges, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning
<pb facs="tcp:59471:3"/> ſome pieces of Antiquity, that it hath made them Famous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the World, where any thing of Hiſtory is known, or regarded: Witneſs their ſtately Pillars of Braſs, and other Mettals; their coſtly Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and other Monuments erected, all to perpetuate, and celebrate the Memory of their Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> I crave no more liberty than they arrogated, my ſubject being of ſuch a bigneſs, the <hi>Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles</hi> may eaſily be avoided; I may with the more boldneſs make my Addreſs to the Ingenious, hoping with him to be Accepted: As for a carping <hi>Momus,</hi> as I value not what he can ſay in my Favours, ſo I as little regard what he can ſay to the Diſadvantage of my Self or
<pb facs="tcp:59471:3"/> Book. You have here a delectable ſubject, wherein you may have an Idea of One who was the Glory of his Nation, the Honour of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, the Terror of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and the Ornament of all places where he Reſorted: His Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Succeſs you may eaſily perceive; but the ſharpeſt Eye could never fix one Blot or Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh upon his Reputation, from his Birth to his Death.</p>
            <p>I ſhall detain thee no longer in the Entry, hoping that what I have ſaid in theſe few Lines, be made out with advantage in the Book it ſelf; to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59471:4"/>
            <head>The Honourable HISTORY Of the Renowned Champion <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> OF The Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. How St. <hi>Patrick</hi> with other five Champions was wonderfully delivered out of the Cave of the Sorcereſs <hi>Kalib,</hi> by St. <hi>George</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath ever been held in great eſteem amongſt all Nations, to preſerve a due Veneration of their Heroes, Patriots, and Noble Champions; their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories have been ſo pretious to them, that many and great Battels have been fought in Honour of the particular Tutelars of divers Kingdoms.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59471:5"/>
               <p>This makes <hi>Greece</hi> ſtill proud of her great <hi>Achilles, Rome</hi> of her <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caeſars;</hi> with no leſs reaſon do the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Honour the memory of the Victorious St. <hi>George, Spain</hi> of her <hi>Jago. France</hi> of St. <hi>Dennis, Scotland</hi> of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Croſs they Annually wear in his Comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oration; As the <hi>Britains</hi> Celebrate their St. <hi>Davids</hi> Day, by wearing a Leek in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onour of him: And why the <hi>Hibernian</hi> Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on ſhould not receive his juſt and due Commemoration, I think little can be objected againſt it, but rather all muſt yield to the Iuſtneſs and Equality of ſo Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Remembrance; eſpecially ſeeing the fame of his mighty Valour, and puiſſant Courage runs in an equal, if not a larger Stream than the reſt of his Fellows.</p>
               <p>We ſhall therefore, to give him his proper Applauſe, Diſcourſe of his great Atcheivements, Mighty Proweſs, Wonderful Succeſſes, and Strange Adventures, as they offer themſelves unto us ſeparately and apart from the other ſix; and herein we ſhall ſtrictly keep to the beſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in this caſe Errant.</p>
               <p>Know therefore, that the Seven Champions of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> which we juſt now recited, were extant in the World at one and the ſame time; only the Heroick St. <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> came laſt by Birth; but upon that Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he was fortunately the occaſion of all the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59471:5"/> wonders performed by the other ſix, as the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Relation will at large inform you.</p>
               <p>In the Year of our Redemption three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sixty one, One <hi>Calphurnius</hi> or <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurcuus</hi> a man Honorable and well Eſteemed, begat a Son of <hi>Concheſſa</hi> his Wife, who when he was Baptized was called <hi>Suchar</hi> or <hi>Socher,</hi> afterward called by St. <hi>Germanus, Magonius;</hi> but at laſt <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> called him <hi>Patrick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Patrick</hi> was born upon the Coaſt of <hi>Britain,</hi> in a place called by the Antients <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnia</hi> or <hi>Hiburnia.</hi> And being yet a Child, was inſtructed in ſuch parts of Learning as his tender years were capable of; wherein he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, to the Admiration of ſuch as knew him, till that upon a time the <hi>Iriſh</hi> having made an Inroad upon that Country, carried away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of the Spoil, a great many Children and Young Men, of which Number Young <hi>Patrick</hi> being but a Stripling, had the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; or rather the fortune to make one.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pirate</hi> (for ſuch they were that carried them away) having arrived ſafe at their own Country, and divided the Spoyl; He to whoſe ſhare <hi>Patrick</hi> ſell, ſold him to an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Man, who preſently ſet him to keep a Herd of Swine, which grieved the Youth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly: Yet ſeeing no viſible way under Heaven, whereby he could be delivered, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59471:6"/> to bear his burden patiently, and to put all his Confidence in God, that in due time he would find out a way to inlarge him from that Slavery under which he was. Six years continued he in this condition; at the end of which time, Divine providence directed him (as he was in the Field feeding the Swine) where there was a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hidden in the Earth, which when he had found; his next care was, to try if by its means he might work out his deliverance: Therefore he came to his Maſter, inſinuating, that if he ſhould accept of a little Money, to let him go, he thought he could procure it; the other readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepts the Motion; ſo that having payed him down a round Sum of his new-found Gold, he freely diſcharged him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patrick</hi> being now releaſed from his bondage, did not ſtand long debating what to do, but lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold on the firſt opportunity, he returned home to his Native Country, to the great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of his Friends and former Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, being almoſt hopeleſs ever to ſee him again. Yet the Ioy which he had to ſee his Friends, was not without mixture of Grief and Sorrow; for in his Abſence a grievous and deadly Hereſie had crept in into the Country, which with its venemous plague infected the minds of a great many People. This Hereſie was headed by <hi>Pelagius,</hi> that Viperous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Grace of God.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59471:6"/>
               <p>This conſuming flame ſtill growing, means were uſed by the more Orthodox Divines of that time for its extinguiſhing; for which end St. <hi>Jermanus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aixen,</hi> and St. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Trecaſs</hi> came to <hi>Britain,</hi> who Laboured mightily to inform the People, and to reclaim them from their Errors; <hi>Patrick</hi> having occaſion to hear St. <hi>Jermanus</hi> Preach, was exceedingly taken with him: Therefore having inſinuated himſelf into his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, became very familiar with him, and gave himſelf, for many Years, to be inſtructed by him, being as yet called <hi>Magonius;</hi> his only Study was ſupernatural knowledge, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite withdrawn himſelf from the Cares and Vexations of the World, he totally dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eated himſelf to Piety and Devotion.</p>
               <p>Having thus by long and ſerious Study ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed himſelf with Learning, he reſolved to imploy his Talent among the Poor ignorant <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whoſe darkneſs and miſery he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly acquainted with: Wherefore he takes a Iourny to <hi>Rome,</hi> and caſts himſelf at <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtines</hi> feet, beſeeching him that he would uſe ſome means for inſtructing that People, who though they were Ignorant, yet were tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and might be informed; <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> highly applauded his requeſt, imploying himſelf as the fitteſt Inſtrument to manage the Work. Having likewiſe inveſted him in the Prieſtly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59471:7"/> Office, he called his Name <hi>Patricius,</hi> hoping he would be a Spiritual Father to many, and ſo diſpatched him for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Holy Man returned about the Year 425. of whoſe Arrival, when the Inhabitants were certified, they came in vaſt Multitudes to ſee him; for although ſome there were among them that endeavoured to put him out of the Country, yet the far greater part of the People did cleave to him, as to a Father; for there were in him many qualifications ſufficient to conciliate their reſpects to him, being eloquent without affectation, humble without diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; grave without ſullenneſs: Add to theſe, his great dexterity in ſpeaking the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Language, wherein he was ſhort of none of the Natives; alſo his Acquaintance with their Manners, whereby he had a great advantage for further gaining of them; but that which gave him moſt ſucceſs, was the ſingular bleſſing of God upon his labours, by which in a ſhort time he gained a vaſt Multitude of Men and Women to the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Patrick</hi> like a faithful Sheepherd watches over his Flock daily, inſtructing young Converts in the Knowledg of Chriſt, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning others in the Faith, and exhorting all to a ſtrict and auſtere Life. Alſo, he ſtrenuouſly refuted the Errors of Hereticks, and confounded the Gainſaying Magitians; he often viſited the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59471:7"/> Sick upon their Beds, nouriſhing their minds with Goſpel-Food: ſometimes alſo, when he ſaw it needful, he with his Prayers Healed their Bodies of their Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Patrick</hi> followed this courſe of Life, many there were who with a perverſe mind op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Doctrine, others as it were haulting betwixt two opinions, not knowing which to follow, greatly deſiring of the Holy Man, that he would ſhew them ſome Viſible Sign of theſe Ioyes of Heaven, and Torments of Hell, which he Preached; he hearing this, did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf a for little ſpace, and having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed himſelf to God, he earneſtly beſought him that for once he would condeſcend to their requeſt. The Almighty was not Deaf to his Prayers, by whoſe inſpiration, he went towards the South parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> there in a deſolate place he found a Cave; into which, if any did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there ſeemed to appear to them moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apparitions in divers and fearful ſhapes; of which, <hi>Girald</hi> of <hi>Wells</hi> who lived about the Year One Thouſand One Hundred and Eighty, Writes thus: There is, ſaith he, a place in the further Parts of <hi>Neſter,</hi> wherein there is an Iſland divided into two parts, whereof one part is very Religious, having a large Church, which is Famous for the concourſe of <hi>Engliſh</hi> to it. The other part being Wild and Vninhabited, is ſaid to be poſſeſſed only
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59471:8"/> by <hi>Daemons,</hi> there they are viſibly ſeen to march up and down in great Troops. This Author adds further, that it is reported, that if one be enjoyned for Penance to ſuſtain the Torments of this place, he ſhall feel no infernal torments, except he afterward commit greater ſins than theſe, for which he did his Penance. This place is by the Inhabitants of the Country called <hi>Patricks Purgatory.</hi> Yet <hi>Patrick</hi> did by his indefatigable Preaching of the Word, and frequent Reaſonings with thoſe Savages, powertuny convince them of the Reality, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> both of the enjoyments of the Saints in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Damned in Hell; for which he was very Famous in his Generation.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ar of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fifty and Eight, whoſe Body was aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rward found, together with the Bodies of St. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lumb,</hi> and St. <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> in the City of <hi>Duns</hi> in <hi>Ulſter,</hi> about the Year One Thouſand One Hundred Seventy Six; as the ſame Author doth witneſs; who alſo Labours to prove, that by the Vertue of this Patron; It came to paſs, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ground can neither breed nor nouriſh any Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Creature.</p>
               <p>He further Writeth, that among their other Wooden Relicks, they have one which they call the Club of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which is eſteemed very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59471:8"/> for it is thought that with it St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> baniſhed all venemous Creatures from the Iſland. Another of his Relicks was a Trumpet, which the ſame Author ſaith a <hi>Pedler</hi> carried about with him, telling the People, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he came, that for Reverence to the Saint, none durſt Sound it: But being upon a day in a Village where a great many People Flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about him, he according to his cuſtom held out the Trumpet to them to kiſs it: but a Prieſt called <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſtanding in the Crowd, ſnatcht it out of his hand, and ſet to his Mouth to Sound with it; but as the Story goes, was preſently ſo ſtruck, that his mouth turned awry even to his Ear, ſo as he could hardly ſpeak; yea further, that he fell into ſuch a Lethargy, that he ſcarcely remembered he had a Name; though he was formerly a very Learned Man, yet was he ſo blaſted, that when he recovered ſomewhat of his Senſes, he was forced (though an Old Man) to begin like a Child to learn the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>There was in thoſe dayes a mighty Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſs named <hi>Kalyb,</hi> who for the Cloſer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of her Enchantments, was retired from Human Society, into a Cave, remote from all Walks, Roads, or Habitations, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with thick Groves, ſolitary Deſarts, mighty Thickets, and unfrequented Solitudes, where ſhe had fitter opportunity to put her
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59471:9"/> vile Practices in Execution. In this place ſhe had an Enchanted Caſtle, wherein ſhe ſhut up all thoſe her Fiendly-Power could Seize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhe feared or ſuſpected might be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental of doing any good in the World: Eſpecially Men of great Courage, and Noble minds, which alwayes go hand in hand; and that is the reaſon why Men of Valour ſeek out brave Enterprizes, and Heroick Exploits: Such as the relieving the Diſtreſſed, diſſolving the Charms of Witches, and Oppoſing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is hurtful to Mankind. On theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations this malitious Enchantreſs employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her utmoſt cunning, (which ſhe arrived to by a conſtant Familiarity with Infernal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in theſe Dark Receſſes) to find out the Nativities of Children, whoſe Stars promiſed great things, and whom the Fates had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to great and Famous Exploits: and no ſooner had ſhe diſcovered the happy Birth of any ſuch like Champion, but ſtrait ſhe fell to her Magick, and Spells; and by her Emiſaries or Familiars, would lurch them into her Clutches, and confine them by her Enchantments from that Chivalry, which otherwiſe the World might expect of them. By theſe Artifices ſhe had already ſurprized into her Cuſtody all the Seven, except the Valiant St. <hi>George,</hi> whom the good Stars had determined to be the deliverer of all the reſt.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59471:9"/> She Seized them all in their Minority and Childhood, or rather Infancy; for in the Night when their Drowſy Nurſes were a ſleep, this powerful Enchantreſs would ſend her Friends that ſhould Spirit them away to her Magical Cell; leaving their diſtreſſed Parents to tear themſelves with Fruitleſs Lamentations.</p>
               <p>In this Brazen Inchanted Caſtle they ſpent their time, ſhut up from the Comfort and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of their dear Friends and Parents, and all the Dalliances attending the Children of Great Princes, (for of no leſs Stock were theſe Mighty Champions deſcended) and confined to the Society of Batts, the Muſical Harmony of Owles and Ravens, Ioyned with a Conſort of Froggs croaking, Adders hiſſing, Wolves howling; and ſuch a diſmal noiſe as might well beget in them an Opinion, that they were no better than on the Confines of Hell.</p>
               <p>When one day walking in the Hall of their Magical Covent, where, amongſt many other Monſtrous Figures, was the Picture of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Hydra</hi> with the Seaven Heads; Sayes the Wiſe <hi>Patrick</hi> to his Fellow Priſoners, <hi>Methinks this ſilly Serpent very well repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents our Condition, (only ſhe hath one head too many) who like ſo many heads are join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a noiſom Body, and confined to an ugly deformed ſhape; and yet theſe heads are Crowned as if they were Kings or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59471:10"/> at leaſt, and one of them ſeems as a ſleep, which perhaps may ſignify another Worthy, not yet arrived to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſt with very great attention hearkened to the Admirable Interpretation the Sagatious Champion had made of that Dreadful Figure, and with no leſs aſtoniſhment, gave ear to the ſtrange Explanations he made of divers other Monſtrous repreſentations, which inſtead of Ornaments were fixed around the Walls of the Brazen Caſtle, which was indeed all the Diverſion theſe Great and Generous Heroes had to entertain themſelves withal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There (inſtead of Curious Tapiſtry, wherein the ſoft Hiſtory of the <hi>Arcadian</hi> Loves were Expreſſed, and inſtead of Battels, Landskips, Proſpects and Hiſtories with which the Galleries of their Palaces were adorned:) they ſaw the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Gaſtly <hi>Proſerpine,</hi> Fell <hi>Rhadaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> or Fiery <hi>Alecto;</hi> their Eyes were blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſhapes of Helliſh Furies, Horrid Monſters, or cruel Murthers: Their Ears, inſtead of the Charming Sweetneſs of well tuned Muſick, were accoſted with yellings of Spirits, groanings of thoſe that were bound in the Fetters of <hi>Kalybs</hi> Enchantments, howlings of terrible Fiery Wolves, Roaring of Devils; and all the diſtaſtful noiſes imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: So that many times you might have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59471:10"/> ſeen the <hi>French</hi> Champion ſtop his Ears with Muſhrooms to keep out the Horrour of the frightful ſound. But the Magnanimous <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> (who in his Childhood had been uſed to Conquer <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wolves, and in queſt of Beaſts of Prey to hunt through the fouleſt and moſt noiſom Boggs) little daunted at theſe hideous Spectacles, often by his great Courage and Bravery, Buoyd up the Spirits of his dejected Companions: and would recount to them the Labours of <hi>Hercules,</hi> the Travels of <hi>Eneas,</hi> and ſet before them the Examples of Great and Couragious Champions, who by their prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs had Conquered all Difficulties: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he perſwaded them with an Vndaunted ſtedfaſtneſs to contemn the Misfortunes of this Witchy Cave; not doubting, but their kinder Stars would direct a way out of that diſmal Labyrinth.</p>
               <p>One day it happened, that the Sorcereſs (having ſate up in Conſult the night before with her Acquaintance of the other World, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Drank a doſe or two too much of <hi>Lethe,</hi> in drinking Healths to <hi>Pluto</hi>) was laid to ſleep away her potation, and in that Interval the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Champion, who had been divers Years ſhut up in a Recluſe in that Enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Caſtle) took the Freedom to view the Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Brazen Tower; he had ſeen the Garden, which ſwarmed with Baſilisks,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59471:11"/> Crocadiles, Aſpes, Scorpions, and all ſorts of venemous Serpents; In the midſt, a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fed by the River Stix, wherein they ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed their Flaming poiſonous Tongues. On the Trees (inſtead of Fruit) hung the Sculs of Dead Men that had been devoured by theſe Monſters: After having obſerved abundance more of theſe Hideous Spectacles, he came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Yard, where the Dogs were that guarded the Caſtle; ſome whereof had heads like Bulls, and were derived of the Centawrs; others had three or four heads, which the Witch had obtained of the race of <hi>Cerberus</hi> the Dog of Hell; ſome had Flaming Tongues, others Tallons like Eagles; with divers other forms too tedious here to recite: but ſuch was the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of this Famous Champion, that all crowched and fawned whileſt he paſt them by. This Court led him into the great Hall where the other ſix Heroes were confined. At his entrance they all ſtood amazed, ſuppoſing ſome Diety had been come to viſit them, until our brave St. <hi>Patrick</hi> aſſuming his Native Courage, thus addreſs'd himſelf to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be not abaſhed, moſt Noble Partners, at the preſence of this Extraordinary Perſon whom here you ſee; for ſince his coming into this Room, it hath been revealed unto me, that this muſt be the moſt Famous, Valiant, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59471:11"/> Renowned Champion of</hi> England, <hi>whom for our Deliverance, our Angels have ſent unto this place; and this doubtleſs (continued he) is him that was ſignifyed by the ſeventh head we ſaw on yonder Beaſt, which ſeemed to us as if aſleep.</hi> At which, caſting their Eyes towards the Figure of the <hi>Hydra,</hi> they perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that that head ſeemed to be awake, and was lifted up above the reſt; whereupon they all made their Obeiſance to the brave St. <hi>George,</hi> and were by him comforted with promiſes to do his utmoſt towards their Enlargement from that Barbarous, and Miſerable place. Then turning himſelf unto our Famous St. <hi>Patrick, Sir</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Your Extraordinary Courage, and great skill in Revelations, give me Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion particularly to apply my ſelf to you; beſides, my good Genius doth aſſure me you are of the Antient, hardy</hi> Hibernian <hi>Race; and that with your Sword you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſuch Wonderful Adventures, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Deeds, as ſhall enroll you in the Bed of Immortal Honour, and juſtly Entitle you the</hi> Champion <hi>of your Native Country.</hi> Something he added to the reſt, but that not being to our purpoſe, we Omit; only that he told them he would go and put ſuch a deſign in Execution, as ſhould ſpeedily accompliſh their deſired Enlargement.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59471:12"/>
               <p>Then taking his leave of them, he retired to his own Quarter, where he had remained a very litle while, before the Cruel Sorcereſs <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib</hi> came unto him; and feeling yet about her the warm effects of her laſt-Nights Debauch; ſhe could not forbear expreſſing her Amours to the Young Knight; and although ſhe had often, without Succeſs, made uſe of the ſame Importunities with the other Six (eſpecially our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Hero) who with manly Bravery withſtood her laſcivious Aſſaults; yet at the ſight of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spark, ſhe fell to her old pulling, and found in her ſelf a Violent Inclination to a farther Intimacy, which in ſuch words ſhe uttered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt puiſſant Knight, You know me to be Lady of this mighty Caſtle; and that there is nothing in the Power of Hell but I can accompliſh; for not only all theſe Fell and Dreadful Monſters reſiding in this Valley, but even the Fiends themſelves Obey me. Nor there any thing ſo difficult, but for the ſake of your Love, I will perform: Command then Noble Prince, and you ſhall ſoon ſee how ready your</hi> Kalyb <hi>is to obey you; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afford me the ſweet Embraces of your Excellent Perſon, and all that I am, or have, is at your Princely Feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59471:12"/>
               <p>At this the Youthful Champion ſeemed to be ſomewhat ſurprized; until recollecting with himſelf, that ſeemingly to cheriſh her Affection, would be the only way to accompliſh his deſigns, for by that means ſhe would be ingaged to a greater Confidence in him, and the more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant to his purpoſe: He therefore made her this Reply.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mighty Princeſs, Since by your Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary bounty, I have found a Noble Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in your Pallace, beyond the ſtretch of my ſlender Memory to remember; and by your great kindneſs, have had Information of my Parentage and Quallity: Beſides the Mighty Favour of your High Affection; It would be Stupendious Ingratitude in me, not to Embrace ſo Noble a Friendſhip: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be aſſured, Great Lady, That the ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your Captive ſhall be always proſtrate to your Command.</hi> Then making a very graceful Conge, he Imprinted in her a ſtrong belief, that her Charm had taken; wherefore taking him by the hand, ſhe led him round the Battlements of her Pallace, giving him a large proſpect of vaſt Dominions and Territories; then leading him on through many Galleries, at length ſhe brought him to a Grot or Cave, wherein was a large Vault in the faſhion of a Stately Hall: it was covered with mighty
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59471:13"/> Groves of decayed Pepplers, and as dark as night: But this darkneſs was Vanquiſhed by a number of <hi>Goblins,</hi> who with Flambeas ſtood round the Room. Here ſhe gave him an Entertainment of her Magical Diverſions, cauſing many Fairy Spirits to <hi>Maſquerade</hi> it to the Muſick of Beetles and Graſs-hoppers: Then came a Troop of Satyrs, footing it to the Noiſe of their own Bagpipes, they having learnt that Inſtrument of <hi>Pan;</hi> at laſt came in a kind of jolly fellow clod in Ivie, and a ſort of Muſhromes, having twenty Iacks with Wiſps dancing in before him; and ſeeming to ſtagger, or rather ſtumble into the Hall, he entertained them with the following Song.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>SONG.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>FRom <hi>Oberon,</hi> and <hi>Fairy-Land,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>The King of Ghoſts, and Goblins there</l>
                              <l>Mad <hi>Robin</hi> I, at his command</l>
                              <l>Am come to view your Nights-Sports here;</l>
                              <l>What Revel Rout</l>
                              <l>You keep about</l>
                              <l>In e'ry Corner where I go,</l>
                              <l>Mad <hi>Robin</hi> I,</l>
                              <l>Your Feats will ſpy,</l>
                              <l>And fear you home with Ho, ho, ho!</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59471:13"/>
                              <l>If any Wanderer I do meet</l>
                              <l>That from his Night-Sports doth trudge home,</l>
                              <l>With Counterfeiting Voice I greet,</l>
                              <l>And cauſe them on with me to Roam;</l>
                              <l>O'er Hedge, o'er Lands,</l>
                              <l>Through Pools, thro' Ponds,</l>
                              <l>O're Hill and Dale, both high and low:</l>
                              <l>And when I have done</l>
                              <l>Away I run,</l>
                              <l>And leave them laughing, Ho, ho, ho!</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Sometimes I meet them like a <hi>Man,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>Sometimes an <hi>Ox,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Hound,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>And to a <hi>Horſe</hi> I turn me can,</l>
                              <l>To trip and dance about them round:</l>
                              <l>If any dare</l>
                              <l>My back to ſtride,</l>
                              <l>More ſwift than Winde, away I go,</l>
                              <l>O'er Hedge, o'er Lands,</l>
                              <l>Through Pools, thro' Ponds,</l>
                              <l>And leave them laughing, Ho, ho, ho!</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>When Lads and Laſſes merry be</l>
                              <l>With Poſſets, and with Junkets fine,</l>
                              <l>Unſeen of all the Company,</l>
                              <l>I eat their Cake, and drink their Wine;</l>
                              <l>And to make Sport,</l>
                              <l>I Fart and Snort,</l>
                              <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59471:14"/>
                              <l>And out the Candles I do blow;</l>
                              <l>The Maids I kiſs,</l>
                              <l>They Skrick! Who's this?</l>
                              <l>I nought reply, but, Ho, ho, ho!</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Song ended, all the <hi>Faries, Goblins,</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> in the Hall, ſet up a Levit with Hunting Horns of all ſizes; which they did with ſo ſtrong a Blaſt, that by the Ecchoing of the Vault and Caves, you would have thought all the Noiſes in the World had been contracted into that Cell. This being performed, the Witch diſmiſſed her Familiars, and Conducting the undaunted Knight to her own Apartment, She gave her Servants Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to lay her Bed in a low Parlour, and Commanded the Room to be ſtrewed with Penſies, Vervam, Dill, and Yerrow; there being in theſe Herbs a Magical Virtue inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Feat; thence taking the Governour of her heart into her Cloſſet, ſhe took a Bottle of <hi>Nepenthe,</hi> which had many years been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and was found out by <hi>Juno</hi> to incline <hi>Paris</hi> to affect her: here taking firſt a large ſoop her ſelf, ſhe poured out a Glaſs full for St. <hi>George;</hi> whoſe Natural Signature had arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him againſt all Inchantments whatever; therefore the Knight, without Heſitation, drank it off, naming it a Health to <hi>Kalyb's</hi> beſts affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhe took in ſuch kind part, that ſitting
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59471:14"/> down on her Coutch, ſhe drew the Valiant Youth to her ſide; and falling into another Amou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Pang, She had much ado to put off the Violence of her Paſſion until Bed time: But the fumes of her laſt Doſe working on the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of her laſt-nights Potation, at laſt clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her eyes, which the ſubtile Champion ſoon obſerving, he laid hold on a Silver wand which lay in the Cloſet, whereon was Engraven this Motto,
<q>
                     <l>He that hath this, may all things Do,</l>
                     <l>May ſpoil the Charm, and Charmer too.</l>
                  </q> Vpon which, St. <hi>George</hi> Immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded this to be the Enchanted Rod, by which ſhe wrought all her Magical Spells; and heartily glad of ſuch an oppertunity, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to try the Experiment of it on her ſelf; wherefore with that Wand ſtroaking her gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly over the Eye-lids, he ſealed them for ever opening again, and Charmed her into ſuch a Dead Lethargy, that ſhe never more awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>St. George delivering St. Patrick and the other five champions form the cave of the Sorceress Kalyb</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Divers Caves alſo that had Men, and Children, ſhut up in them many Years, of themſelves flew open, and there was a Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Goal-Delivery, of all ſuch as the Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Kalyb</hi> had Confined; for at the minute of her Death, her Power ceaſed, nor was there any longer force of her Charms.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59471:15"/>
               <p>All the deformed Spirits, Hideous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, dreadful Noiſes, and Venomous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Vaniſhed, and a beautiful Serenity dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it ſelf over the whole Valley. The Graſs aſſumed its Verdure, the Flowers their Odour, the Birds their Harmonious Warb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the Fountains again recovered their Chriſtalline Purity, and all things returned to their Native Order and Beauty.</p>
               <p>Thus was the Mighty Inchantment of the Famous <hi>Kalyb</hi> diſſolved; whilſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits hurryed her miſerable Carkaſs into the Dreadful Torments of a Wretched Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59471:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. The Valiant St. <hi>Patrick</hi> taketh leave of the other ſix Champions; what happened to him after his departure.</head>
               <p>THe Heroick St. <hi>Patrick</hi> perceiving himſelf now at liberty from thoſe Witchy bonds which had a long time confined him, and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the great performances of his Sword; thought fit to loſe no longer time, but to ſeek out ſuch Adventures as might Enrole his Name amongſt the Chiefeſt Worthies: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſpake to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Champion after this manner;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Right Noble and Victorious St.</hi> George, <hi>ſince it hath pleaſed our better Stars to make you the Glorious Inſtrument of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from the miſerable Enchantment wherein we were tyed; and you ſeem to be ſent from Heaven to us, as our Guardian-Angel; give me leave (after repeating my Unfeigned thanks for your ſo unparalleld favour) to aſſure you, that I think the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of our Lives cannot be better Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, than in the Service of our Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Benefactor; and therefore we will follow your Conduct, and Commands, upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59471:16"/> and Acknowledge it as our greateſt happineſs to ſerve ſo Generous a Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which Speech, the other Five having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their joynt Conſent, The moſt Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous St. <hi>George</hi> having with great Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity received their Complement, made this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Renowned</hi> Iriſh <hi>Knight, Whoſe unmatcht Courtiſie (without the Acheivements of thy Armes) might Entitle thee</hi> Conquerour of the World; <hi>and you my Fellow Souldiers, who with ſo great Affection have offered your kindneſs to me: You may be well aſſured, that it was not for my ſake, this great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle hath been wrought, but for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral benefit of all Mankind, who need the aſſiſtance of your Valours: Let us then ſhape divers Courſes, and ſearch out Glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements in the furthermoſt part of the World: Let us divide our ſelves, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Monuments to our High Courages in all the Habitable parts of the Globe; making the moſt Remote and Barbarous Provinces pay Tribute to the Memory of the Seaven Mighty Champions of</hi> Europe. <hi>And as for You thrice Noble</hi> Patrick, <hi>where ever the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Harp ſhall ſound, your Fame ſhall be recorded by the beſt skill of deviceful Bards, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59471:17"/> ſmooth-Tongued Rythmers; our ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countries ſhall wear Badges of Honour to our Memories, and the greateſt Knights take their Nobility from the Names of our Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Rhetorical Speech of St. <hi>Georges</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended; the Active <hi>Iriſh</hi> Knight thought long to have his Spurs on; wherefore calling to him one <hi>Mac,</hi> a Servant of his, that had been ſhut up with others in the Inchanted Rock; he gave him order to go and provide Horſes for himſelf, and the other ſix Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to bring them to the Brazen Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with all Expedition. <hi>Mac</hi> readily Obeying his Lords Commands, was gone in a trice. In the mean time the Worthy Knights ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Rooms of the Caſtle, found all manner of Rich and Coſtly Furniture, with Princely Habiliments of War, which the damn'd Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs had laid up, having belonged to Princes, which ſhe had Deviliſhly made away in her Enchanted Cell. There were carved <hi>Indian</hi> Lances, <hi>Turky</hi> Bows, <hi>Tartarian</hi> Darts, <hi>Toledo</hi> Swords, <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Piſtols, <hi>Leather</hi> Carbines; and ſo many ſorts of Martial En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, ſo quaintly deviſed, that it would have puſſed all the <hi>Virtuoſo's</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> to have mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Invention. There were Drums and Trumpets that would beat and ſound of their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59471:17"/> own accord, to animate the Valiant to Battle. Muſquetoons and Blunderbuſs's that would charge and diſcharge themſelves ſeaven or eight times following: There were Likewiſe, Breaſt-plates, Reins, Croupers, and Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all ſorts; ſome whereon the Pencil had ſhewed its beſt Art; others where the Needle hath tryed its utmoſt skill: for on ſome were the Loves of <hi>Pyramus,</hi> and <hi>Thisbie;</hi> on others <hi>Dido</hi> hanging her ſelf for <hi>Eneus,</hi> then <hi>Venus</hi> tearing her treſſes for loſs of <hi>Adonis; Juno</hi> looking through her fingers at the Rapes of <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and on one was Prophetically drawn St. <hi>George</hi> and the Dragon, with Damoſel by: Beſides, a number of Impreſſes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and curious Stories of like Nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to fire the Courage of the moſt mortified Knight alive.</p>
               <p>They had ſcarcely choſen out of the Armory, what was ſuitable to their ſeveral Phanſies and Occaſions, before <hi>Mac</hi> was returned with the Horſes; which were ſuch, that if <hi>Barbary</hi> were ranſacked for Beauty, or <hi>Germany</hi> for ſtrength, they could not have been matcht; Nor is it ſtrange, that they were brought ſo ſuddainly; for this being an Age of Miracles, St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Groom met them on the Road coming to the Caſtle of their own accord, and ready marked to their hand; for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Knights was branded with an Harp; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59471:18"/> Garter; the <hi>Scots,</hi> with a Croſs Saltier; the <hi>Britains</hi> with a Leek; The <hi>Italians</hi> with a Tarantula; The <hi>Spaniards</hi> with a Goat; and <hi>Monſiers</hi> with the Scratches: So that it was eaſie to determine which <hi>Jennet</hi> belonged to each Champion.</p>
               <p>There was not need of much trouble to put on their ſeveral furnitures; for they fitted ſo exactly, as if they had been made on purpoſe; they were all very Sumptuous, Rich, and of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Device. I ſhall only take notice of the Capariſon of our Noble St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> whoſe Impreſs was an <hi>Orpheus</hi> playing on an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Harp, with a number of Sheep and Bullocks feeding on the Mountaines by. His Motto was,
<q>Beware the Wolf.</q> Now being all mounted on their fiery Steeds, which ſeemed as ſo many Pegaſus's, or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritors of the Sun; and having marched beyond the bounds of the Caſtle: where having caſt Lots which ſhould make the firſt Adventure, the Lot fell to our Noble Champion St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick;</hi> who in a very Knightly Oration, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to affirm Amity with one another; and that they ſhould employ their Valiant Swords in Honour of their Native Countries; promiſing withall, that if either of their perſons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59471:18"/> required his Service, he would on the leaſt notice not fail to come to their Aid and Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Thus having Mutually Embraced, and taken leave of one another, they ſeparated themſelves; each one taking his courſe, as his particular Genius prompted him: Our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion bending the Courſe of his Travails to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North, where he had underſtood, that a Knight of Extraordinary proweſs, had belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured a very Beautiful and Excellent Lady in her own Caſtle, with reſolution to force her thence to Marry him, notwithſtanding ſhe had plighted her Faith to another Lord; who tho much Inferiour to him in the Bounties of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, had by far the preheminence of him in Perſonal Endowments, and eſpecially in the Eſteem and good Affection of the fair <hi>Climena,</hi> (for ſo was the Lady called) ſo that the moſt Accompliſht <hi>Philadon</hi> had already ſecured the main fortreſs, whilſt in vain his wretched Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val <hi>Lymas</hi> lay Storming of the Out-works.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>St. Patrick meeting Lord Olinder by the bank of the river</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Knight <hi>(ſaid he) for ſo your Armes and Equipage beſpeaks you to be; I well perceive you are a Stranger in theſe Parts; and the time of the Evening now requires a due refreſhment after your Travels, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you pleaſe to accept of ſuch a Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as my Country Manſion doth afford; I ſhall acknowledg it an Honour to my Houſe, and you ſhall as freely command there, as if you were in your own Inn: Beſides, you muſt underſtand, that here is no Village for your Reception, in divers Miles of this place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Patrick</hi> having with due acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accepted <hi>Olindors</hi> Generous Offer,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59471:20"/> Alighted off his Horſe, and taking the Reins in his hand, he walked together with his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hoſt towards his Stately Habitation. They had gon but little more than a Furlong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Walks opened them a proſpect to the Front of the Building, which ſtood on a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle aſcent of ground looking over the pleaſant Fields we but now deſcribed. The entrance was raiſed on Pillars of Marble, with Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtals and Capjters of Burniſhed Braſs, which gave a luſtre like ſhining Gold; within the entrance was a Terras ſupported with Pillars of Iet, upon a Pavement of divers Culler'd Marble moſt Artiffcially layd in Chequer Work, on each ſide a green Court ſet with Mirtles, Oranges, and Pines. The Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf was raiſed with Porphyrie, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labaſter Curiouſly ſet in Vniform Squares, or Pains. A little before they came to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, at a ſmall diſtance on the left hand was the Stable; a ſtructure not unſuitable to the Grandure of the reſt, but as much as any thing ſpoke the Magnificence of the Owner; beſides carved ſtalls for a hundred Horſes, there was in one part a Mew appointed where the Hawks were kept, which in their ſeveral Seaſons brought the Duck, the Quail, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, and Plover to their Maſters Table, there were propper Lodgings for the Gromes, and Falconers, beſides Stores for the Proven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59471:21"/> and Rooms wherein the Rich Sadles, Capariſons, Arms, and Furniture was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept: So many perquiſites ſwelled the Stables almoſt to the Bulk of the dwelling Houſe, which was hardly diſtinguiſhable from the other in figure; only that it lifted its Lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty head above it.</p>
               <p>Near the ſame diſtance from the entrance on the Right hand was a Curious Fountain, repreſenting the Famous River <hi>Nilus;</hi> for at ſeven heads it diſcharged as many Chriſtal Streams into a Veſſel of Marble, from whence the Water was conveyed to an Adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Pond for waſhing, and refreſhing the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>Near the Dore of the Stables waited ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Grooms, who at a diſtance perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Maſter, ran to attend him, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into their Care the Horſe of our Knightly Travellour. Then the moſt Hoſpitable <hi>Olinder</hi> taking the Noble <hi>Patrick</hi> by the hand, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted him into the moſt Beautiful, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Pallace that ever his eyes had ſeen; They paſſed (through a ſtately Hall whoſe guilded Roof dazled the Eye of the beholder; round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it were curiouſly Painted the Hiſtory of the <hi>Trojan</hi> War, the Mighty Gyants <hi>Aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>path</hi> and St. <hi>Bevis;</hi> and the Famous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat between Captain <hi>Jones,</hi> and the King of <hi>Bombaza;</hi> Their Poſtures and Weapons were
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59471:21"/> ſo lively depainted, you would have thought their Swords and Spears had claſht together;) thence, going through a Gallery which had a Floor of Ceder in-laid with Ebony and Silver, and the Wainſcot of <hi>Indian</hi> Porphirie, curiouſly guilded with Emboſſed work of Gold. They Might ſee there in ſeveral Pieces of admirable Paint, the Honourable and great Atcheivments of the Antient Lords of that princely Seat; from whence entring into a Parlour, whoſe Beauty exceeded all that had yet been ſeen; they ſat down on a Couch of Embroidered Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask richly perfumed, which through a large Caſement of Chriſtal, Entiſed the Eyes of St. <hi>Patrick</hi> into the moſt Beautiful, and Attractive Garden that ever was contrived, by the moſt Exquiſite Artiſt: All that the Fabulous Poets have ſaid in praiſe of their feigned Elyſium falls much ſhort of deſcribing the Charming Glory, and ſweetneſs of this place.</p>
               <p>There were Fountains Contrived with ſuch Admirable Art, that they Saluted your ears with a Conſort of all ſorts of Delectable Muſick, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Copper, expreſſing all the Months of the Year, beſides divers Hiſtorical Figures; but in the midſt ſtood <hi>Flora,</hi> Enthroned as it were in her proper Orb, with all the Fragrancies of Nature round about her. At one ſide was a Wilderneſs for Shady Walks, where (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Clew of Ariadne</hi>) it was hard for a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59471:22"/> Stranger to find the way out again, in one Corner of this was a Grotto where Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Birds of all Sorts Expreſſed the lively Notes of the Natural, and that ſo truely, that Starlings, Black-birds, and Linnets have often reſorted to them, and joyned in their Conſort.</p>
               <p>Whileſt at theſe Excellent Proſpects; Our Champion was Contemplating the Grandure of the Noble <hi>Olindor,</hi> a Page with an humble Reverence, brings into the Room, a Voider of all the Various and Excellent Fruits that ſtately Garden did afford; ſome whereof were Candied with Excellent Art: Of theſe the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Hoſt preſents his Heroick Gueſt, which were of great refreſhment to him after his weary Travail; They had likewiſe of the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Toſcan</hi> Wine, beſides Cordials of Admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable Virtue. Then the Page helping off his Armour, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> with the Friendly <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> took a walk towards the Grot, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> further ſide of the Garden, where ſitting dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together, they began to recount their ſevera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Adventures, and to enquire of one anothers For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tunes, Misfortunes, Succeſſes, and Accidents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59471:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. What Diſcourſe happened in the Grot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween St. <hi>Patrick</hi> and <hi>Olindor,</hi> how St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> undertakes the Releaſe of the Lady <hi>Climena;</hi> with ſeveral Adventures that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel him.</head>
               <p>THe Renowned St. <hi>Patrick</hi> being affected with all Imaginable Satisfaction, at the Grandure, Magnificence, and abounding Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie of the Generous <hi>Olindor;</hi> and well knowing ſuch ſumptuous Pallaces, ſplendid Attendants, with the other Gallantries where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that place abounded, could not be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without an anſwerable Revenue: He thought himſelf highly Obliged to pay a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſpect to the Lord of the greateſt Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace he had ever ſeen. Therefore caſting a Princely Aſpect (yet full of Humility) towards the Reverend <hi>Olindor;</hi> he gave him a full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the Direful Accidents already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in relation to himſelf and the other ſix Champions; all that had happened to them in the Enchanted Caſtle of the Magical <hi>Kalyb,</hi> with the wonderful manner of their ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; by the diſolving her Charmes; at which the Good <hi>Olindor</hi> could not forbear to interrupt him in this Sort: <hi>Oh Heavens!</hi> ſaid
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59471:23"/> he, <hi>and is that Helliſh Sorcereſs at laſt puniſhed for her Divelliſh Practiſes; how much is the World Obliged to the Fortune and Bravery of thoſe Worthies, that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed ſo great a Bleſſing? I have heard</hi> (Continued he) <hi>Strange and Dreadful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, of Monſtrous Cruelties, and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes committed by that Lewd Witch; but had never that particular, and ſatisfactory Account, which now even makes my Ears to rejoyce at the hearing, and fills my Chill'd Veins with a diffuſed warmth for Joy of ſo great a Benefit. What Bleſſings may not Mankind hope for from the Glorious Arms of ſuch All-Conquering Heroes, now the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious Stars have already made you Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over the powers of Darkneſs, and Conquerours even of Hell it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Noble <hi>Patrick</hi> could not here forbear to pay an Honourable Acknowledgment to his Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Hoſt, for the great Character he had giv n himſelf and Fellow-Champions, adding, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whatever Courage or Fortune Heaven had made him and his Brother-Champions Maſters of, muſt certainly be at the Devotion of ſuch as the Brave <hi>Olindor;</hi> and that for his part eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, he knew not how in Gratitude he could anſwer the high Obligations conferr'd on him, without laying both his Sword, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59471:23"/> at the Feet of ſo Excellent a Perſon. Alas (replyed <hi>Olindor</hi>) you have laid ſo weighty a Compliment on a declining Old Man, as makes me even ſtoop beneath the weight of it: But Noble Knight (ſaid he) if your Valour call for Exerciſe; there is a Neice of mine, by Name, <hi>Clymena,</hi> that may need the Aid of your Knightly Proweſs: You muſt know Gallant Stranger, that this Lady is Heireſs to a very Large and fertil Territory, yet of a Family whoſe ſtock of Honour far Exceeds the Bounties of their Large Fortunes. At the Age of Fourteen both her Parents were ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to the Elyſian Shades, leaving the Fair <hi>Clymena</hi> to the Tutelage of her Mothers Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; This Gentleman had a Son of his own about ſixteen years of age by name <hi>Philadon,</hi> who is Maſter of as much perſonal Beauty, happy Education, ſweet Diſpoſition, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Courage (perhaps) as any Lad of his Age, only his Eſtate came ſhort of <hi>Clymena's;</hi> but that was largely ſupplyed by the other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments; which made my Young Neice ſo fond of him, that ſhe would never enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a thought of Marrying any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſtill admitted him to all opportunities of Converſation; ſpending their time in ſuch Gentile Diverſions, as were proper for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Quallity: Somtimes his Voice, ſometimes his Recorder muſt make a Conſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59471:24"/> to her well tun'd Lute: Sometimes their wanton Feet would meaſure out an Artificial knot upon the plain, whilſt one of their Pages proportion'd out their time on a Guittar, or Violin. Sometimes her Phanſie would lead her to the Rivers ſide; where with his Hook and Line, the Charming <hi>Philadon</hi> would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her, bringing the Inhabitants of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Element out of their cold Region, to dance and play in the Sun-ſhine of her Eyes; and what Excellent ſtrains of Courtſhip would the Enamour'd <hi>Philadon</hi> uſe on ſuch occaſions; telling her, that the Sparkling Diamonds of her face beſtowed the guilding, and Enamel on their Silver Seales. Then taking out his Pocket-Whiſtle, he gave his Page a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who in Obedience to that call, ſtreight attended: Sirrah (ſaid his Maſter) do you give this Worthy Knight the Fiſhing Song my Kinſman <hi>Philadon,</hi> made on my Neices going to the Rivers ſide with him, at which the Page taking a Lute taught the ſtrings to anſwer his Voice, whileſt he ſung.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59471:24"/>
                           <head>SONG.</head>
                           <l>Wee'ce gang Early to the Burks ſide,</l>
                           <l>To catch the pretty Fiſhes as they do Glide,</l>
                           <l>And e'ry little Fiſh thy Priſoner ſhall be,</l>
                           <l>For I'ce catch them, and Thou'ſt catch Me.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>There were more of the Verſes, but becauſe of late they have been made common, I ſhall not trouble the Reader with them; but the Page having ended, much to the Satisfaction of the Traveling Knight, (who much admired his graceful performance all the while) the good <hi>Olindor</hi> Aſſumed his Story after this manner.</p>
               <p>But now all thoſe Innocent paſtimes are ceaſed, and their Muſick changed into the Noiſe of Trumpets and Guns, Their Danc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Sallies, and Attaques,</p>
               <p>For ſuddainly in one Night (one <hi>Lymas</hi> a great Lord of the Northern Part, having heard much of the Fortune of <hi>Climena,</hi> and not thinking it fit that any one ſhould be Maſter of ſo great a Treaſure beſide himſelf) came with a mighty force which he had raiſed among his Numerous Tennents; and Accompanied with many young Sparks of his Acquaintance; in an Inſtant ſurrounded the Caſtle, which is the reſidence of theſe two young Lovers; inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59471:25"/> to force the incomparable <hi>Clymena</hi> to his greedy Embraces; many attempts hath he made by Granadoes, Batteries, and other Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes, to enter the Houſe; but by reaſon of its advantageous Scituation, ſtrong Building; and the great care of my Nephew and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, they are ſtill repulſed without ſucceſs: Yeſterday I ſent my only Son (who will be glad of the Honour of your Acquaintance) to gather as many of his Friends and Tennants as he finds willing to engage with him in ſo Honourable an Enterprize; either by force to drive <hi>Lymas</hi> out of our Territories, or at leaſt to relieve the Caſtle until a greater Strength can be raiſed.</p>
               <p>In the Midſt of this diſcourſe a Page gave notice that Supper attended for them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Olindor</hi> taking the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Patron by the hand conducted him to a Spatious Arbour at another corner of the Garden, which was Compoſed of Geſſamines, Mirtles, and Roſes; adjoining to it was an Exquiſite Fountain repreſenting <hi>Helicon,</hi> where the Nine Muſes were Expreſſed in moſt propper Hieroglyphiels caſt in Copper; the Conveyance of the Water was contrived with ſuch Art, that in its paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it made a Muſicall Harmony, as if Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Harpſicals, and Viols, had been in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, and by turning a Cock, they could make it anſwer any time they pleaſed.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59471:25"/>
               <p>The Table was of Allabaſter, whereon they had a moſt Princely Entertainment, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up in Plate and Porcelane of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>China</hi> make; There was Kid; Fowl, and Fiſh, with the Choiceſt Fruits of each kind, according to the proper Seaſon: Wine Richer than ever the <hi>Grecians</hi> offered in Sacrifice to <hi>Bacchus;</hi> whileſt by the Command of <hi>Olindor</hi> on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Pages, ſetting the Fountain in Accord to his Voice, in a mournful Accent ſang this
<q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>SONG.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>AH! Fading Joy, How quickly art thou paſt,</l>
                                 <l>Yet we thy Ruine haſt,</l>
                                 <l>As if the cares of Human life were few,</l>
                                 <l>We ſeek out New,</l>
                                 <l>And follow Fate which would too faſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>See how on every Bow the Birds Expreſs,</l>
                                 <l>In their ſweet Notes, their Happineſs;</l>
                                 <l>They all enjoy, and nothing ſpare;</l>
                                 <l>But on their Mother-Nature lay their Care;</l>
                                 <l>Why then ſhould Man, the Lord of all Below,</l>
                                 <l>Such Troubles chuſe to know,</l>
                                 <l>As none of all his Subjects undergo?</l>
                                 <pb n="44" facs="tcp:59471:26"/>
                                 <l>Hark how the Waters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fall, fall, fall!</l>
                                 <l>And with a murmuring ſound,</l>
                                 <l>Daſh, Daſh upon the Ground,</l>
                                 <l>To gentle Slumbers call.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q> Notwithſtanding the Princely <hi>Patricks</hi> Senſes were all at one time Importuned, and feaſted with the greateſt Delicates Imaginable: His Eyes with the Beautiful proſpect of the Pallace and Garden; his Ears with the Charming Muſick of the Page and Fountain; his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils with the fragrant ſweetneſs of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; his Pallate caſting the ſeveral well-Coockt diſhes, and various Fruits, with which the Table abounded; nor was his ſenſe of feeling un-imployd, for although the ſatisfaction he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from ſo Excellent a Banquet was very great; yet felt he in himſelf a more Ardent deſire to Encounter <hi>Lymas;</hi> and Exerciſe his mighty Armes for the relief of the Beautious <hi>Clymena,</hi> than for ever to enjoy the wanton Luxury of all the Courtly Entertainments imaginable. Dellicacies and Dalliances are uneaſie to Valiant and Heroick Souls, whoſe Magnanimity ſpurs them on alwayes to feats of Arms, and the puiſſant Atcheivments of Chivallry.</p>
               <p>The thrice Noble <hi>Prtrick</hi> could not forbear diſcovering the inward reſentments of his ſoul
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59471:26"/> unto the Brave <hi>Olindor</hi> in this ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excellent Lord</hi> Olindor, <hi>Although the Princely Opulence under which your Table growns, be ſuch as Emperours Pallaces may well envy; and the Entertainment your Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty affords me, far tranſcending all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments I can poſſibly return; yet give me leave to tell you, that the Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity you have put into my hand, to ſerve you in relation to your Neice, and to Hazzard my Life in the ſervice of ſo Worthy a Lord as</hi> Olindor, <hi>infinitely ſurpaſſes all the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction Ariſing from the other conſiderations, ſo that now I covet nothing more than to ſee the Face of</hi> Lymas, <hi>and to call him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the Injuries offered to your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Neice: Doubtleſs</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>he ſhall ſoon be ſenſible of the loſs his own guilt will pull upon him: But</hi> (continued he) <hi>Know Famous</hi> Olindor, <hi>that before I had the good Fortune to meet you by the ſide of your River; I had fully determined to Revenge upon the Impious</hi> Lymas, <hi>the injuries and abuſes done by him to the Lady</hi> Clymena; <hi>for it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Motive that brought me hither: But I muſt acknowledge my Reſolution much Hightened ſince I have had the Relation of her misfortunes from your Lips; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince I underſtand the aliance between
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59471:27"/> your Families to be ſuch, that you are enga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging your Noble Son in the Conflict.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a servant informing St. Patrick and Lord Olinder that Olinder's Son has arrived with reinforcements</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Great Obſervation did all the Strangers take of our Valiant <hi>Patrick,</hi> whoſe Martial Preſence, and Heroick Comportment, made them unanimouſly ſix upon him to be their Leader; but this determination they kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret until the Morning. In the mean time the Prudent <hi>Olindor</hi> gave orders to divers of his principle Servants to be ready to attend his Son on the next dayes March, and to bear him company in the Battel: And to one he gave ſpecial direction to bring him word what was the firſt ſucceſs of the Engagement. All the while the brave <hi>Olinderus</hi> was entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Friends with the Sumptuous Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Fathers Houſe afforded, whileſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral brisk Glaſſes went about to <hi>Clymena's</hi> Health, and the good ſucceſs of their Expedition.</p>
               <p>Thus paſſed they away the Evening, with many diſcourſes relating to the carrying on their Enterpriſe, until the good <hi>Olindor</hi> ſent one of his Gentlemen to acquaint the Noble Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if he pleaſed to repoſe himſelf, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment was ready: So being Conducted by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59471:28"/> divers of the principal Servants with Wax lights in Silver Stands; the Hoſpitable Old Lord would needs attend his Gueſt to his Lodging, as likewiſe did the Young <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and divers of the Principal Nobles: He was led up by a large Stair Caſe of Cedar Richly Carved and Guilded, the Wainſcot adorned with many pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of curious Landskip, and Sea Proſpects of Admirable Art: So that in divers the Wracks were ſo Lively deſcribed, you would have thought you had heard the ſinking Marriners call for help: Some Veſſels ſeemed to be juſt blowing up, where many Bodies appeared mounted up far in the Air, and their Limbs ſcattered with the Violence of the Powder. Within this was a Chamber, where on the Cealing was a Skie moſt Artificially wrought, where Silver <hi>Cynthia,</hi> and her Necturnal Train of glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous Stars and Plannets gave ſo great Luſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as if they had been come there on purpoſe to keep an Alternate watch during the Champi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons Repoſe. It was hung round with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Richeſt <hi>Venetian</hi> Tapſtery of Silk, Silver and Gold; in which was admirably expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Story of <hi>Argalus</hi> and <hi>Perthenia's</hi> Love with their many Adventures; and fatal Trage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, one would have thought by the ſplendour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Chamber, that it had (at leaſt) been th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pallace of bright <hi>Phaebus,</hi> or at leaſt a Receſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> provided for the Poetical Gods.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59471:28"/>
               <p>Thus having brought our Mighty Hero to this Magnificent Lodging; the Moſt Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Olindor,</hi> and the reſt of the Noble Train took their Leaves of him, recommending him to the Quietude of Downy ſlumbers; and having bid each other good night, with the greateſt Civillity the moſt Generous Tongue could Expreſs, the Valiant <hi>Patrick</hi> laid him down on an <hi>Italian</hi> Couch, made of the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt green Silk Damask, under a Canopy of Pearl-Couler Sattin wrought with Flowers of Gold; and Revolving in his mind how to manage the Fortune of the following day: the heavy <hi>Morpheus</hi> with his Leaden Key Lockt up his ſences in ſoul-refreſhing ſleep; and about the midſt of the Night appeared to him the Reſemblance of the Moſt Renowned St. <hi>George,</hi> having on one Arme his Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Garter, on the other his Ruby Croſs, and on his breaſt the figure of the fiery Drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon; his countenance was exceeding Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſuch as it had been, when he Charmed the Enchantreſs <hi>Kalyb:</hi> his preſence was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Amiable and Attractive; and approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſilent Bed of the ſleeping Champion, he thus Accoſted him:
<q>
                     <l>I the Idea of Great <hi>George</hi> am come,</l>
                     <l>To tell thee thou muſt be Baſe <hi>Lymas</hi> doom;</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59471:29"/>
                     <l>Thou Valiant <hi>Patrick</hi> ſhalt his Power Quel,</l>
                     <l>And free <hi>Clymena</hi> from his Magick Spell;</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall thy Sword in <hi>Thracia</hi> raiſe thy Name,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Soultans ſhall Proclaim thy Fame:</l>
                     <l>Kings ſhall in <hi>Patricks</hi> Honour Bages wear,</l>
                     <l>And Mighty Kingdoms to thee Statues Rear.</l>
                  </q> Having ſaid this, the Friendly Spectrum with a ſlow pace left the Room; whilſt St. <hi>Patrick</hi> overjoy'd with the Viſion awaked from his pleaſant ſlumber, &amp; ſtill Imagining his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Champion had been in the Chamber, ſtept out of his Bed to thank him for the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary care he took of his Concernes; but at laſt finding no one, he concluded it was St. <hi>George's</hi> Angel which in ſuch Courteous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had adminiſtred this comfort to him; ſo returning again to his Dormitory, he paſſed the Night in various Cogitations until the Morning.</p>
               <p>But what pen is able to paint out with what Celerity they Addreſſed themſelves to their March; for no ſooner had the gray Ianitor ſprinkled his firſt Attoms of light on the darkned Ayr, foreſhewing the approach of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes</hi> Chariot; but our Warlike <hi>Patrick</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59471:29"/> into the Hall, calling for his Armour, where in a ſhort time the Brave <hi>Olindarus,</hi> with the reſt of the Young Nobles met him. The Grooms had already fitted all the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pages of their Horſes, and made them ready for their Maſters call, and the furious Beaſts ſtood beating the Ground with their hardy Hoofs, as if angry they were not on the March; ſtraight as ſoon as the Knights had compleatly Armed themſelves, the Trumpets ſounded to Horſe; when the mirrour of his Age, the Incomparable <hi>Olindor,</hi> came out of his Chamber to take his leave of his Son, and his Noble Gueſts; <hi>But firſt addreſſing himſelf to the Champion of</hi> Ireland, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the kindneſs of his Stars that at ſuch a time had brought ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Gueſt under under his Roof; adding that the fortune of his Neice, and whole Family depended on his Valour; and that he did not doubt of Victory under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſo Worthy a Cheiftain:</hi> To which he replyed, that he wanted words to expreſs how much he was Obliged to the goodneſs of the moſt generous <hi>Olindor;</hi> but as long as he had a hand able to weild a Sword, it ſhould ſtill be employed in the Service of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Noble Family: Then rendring him his Knightly thanks for the large Bounties of his Houſe, proteſting he thought him the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59471:30"/> moſt Hoſpitable Perſon in the World; the Heroick <hi>Patrick</hi> would needs kiſs his hand, and ſo went to his Horſe; Then with a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenance, embracing his Son, My <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lindarus</hi> (ſaid he) thou art now going into the Field of Honour, to Fight the Battel of an injur'd Lady, my dear Neice; I know that when I was at thy Age, I wanted not Martial Blood; and am only grieved my Age denies me now to bear thee company in ſo brave an Enterprize: Let theſe young Sparks, that in moſt friendly manner bear thee Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to the Wars, ſee proof of the inherent Valour that dwells in <hi>Olindors</hi> Blood; nor ſpake I this as doubting thy brave Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; no, my dear <hi>Olindarus,</hi> thy forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and conduct in this whole Affair, hath given me a large aſſurance of thy readineſs to enter the Liſt, and I doubt not but I ſhall ſee thee return Loaden with Triumphs, to the eternal Honour of thy Noble Anceſtors. Then giving him his Paternal Benediction, he commended them all to the Tutelage of <hi>Minerva,</hi> adviſing them to make choice of the thrice Famous <hi>Patrick</hi> for their Leader; which with one Voice they immediately did, it having been their reſolution the night before: and with loud Acclamations confirmed their Choice, taking it as a good <hi>Omen,</hi> that they had done it by the direction of <hi>Olindor,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59471:30"/> Chariot waited in readineſs to accompany them the firſt two Miles of their March.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Their Equipage at departing from the houſe of <hi>Olindor.</hi> St. <hi>Patrick</hi> arriveth at the Camp, accepteth the Challenge; with what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereupon.</head>
               <p>THe Famous <hi>Patrick</hi> being the Mirrour of true Chivalry, and Grrant Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, was accoutred not unſuitable to his high Quality: He had on a Suit of Armour of <hi>Sythian Steel,</hi> hardened by the <hi>Cyclops</hi> in the Forge of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> folded with joynts of <hi>Braſs,</hi> and ſet with <hi>Studds</hi> of <hi>Gold;</hi> at the bowings of the Arms and Knees, were Figured the heads of four Monſtrous and Terrible Giants, whoſe Eyes ſeemed to ſpartle with burning Fire: on his Breaſt-Plate, he wore a <hi>Harp,</hi> Curiouſly Compoſed of <hi>Diamonds</hi> ſet in <hi>Gold,</hi> and ſtrung with <hi>Pearl;</hi> ſignifying his Native Country, and being the Cognizance thereof. As for his <hi>Target,</hi> it was of the Skins of ſcaly Fiſh, wrought into form by the <hi>Indian Magicians,</hi> and hardened by the Sun, till it was impenitrable, even by Darts pointed with the ſharpeſt <hi>Steel;</hi> he had a <hi>Lance</hi> born by his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59471:31"/> Page, made of Materials ſo tough, as no force could brake, and had for its point the Horn of an <hi>Africane Unicorn,</hi> that would batter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven very Rocks. On his Head was a <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> of the Fineſt <hi>Copper,</hi> Flowered and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid with <hi>Gold,</hi> and ſparkling with <hi>Jems</hi> of divers ſorts; in the Creſt whereof, was ſet a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry large Crimſon <hi>Feather,</hi> ſpangled with <hi>Gold,</hi> which waving down his back, ſeemed like a bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cloud, gently moving before the Wind.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Sword</hi> was ſuppoſed to be the Sire of that in <hi>Weſtminſter-Abby,</hi> in times paſt ſo Terrible to <hi>France;</hi> it had ſo great Virtue, that it would diſſolve Enchantments, brake in ſunder Magical Rocks, and reſiſt the force of Poyſon. This Armour, as you have heard before, was found in the Enchanted Cave of <hi>Kalyb,</hi> and placed there by <hi>Minerva,</hi> to be worn by the moſt Valiant, and Vndaunted <hi>Chevalier</hi> in the World; the proof whereof will app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar in the following Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Equipage of the young <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus,</hi> leſs exquiſite; for his <hi>Armour, Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings</hi> and <hi>Target,</hi> were as Rich as any were ever ſeen in the <hi>Trojan</hi> War; where the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry and Art of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> were to the Life expreſſed. All the other young Noble men his friends, had their ſeveral devices; Some in memory of their Ladies; others pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the deſign of their Enterprize, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59471:31"/> Alluſions proper to their ſeveral Paſſions, and Inclinations. They were all Mounted on Horſes of ſuch Admirable Shape and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as if <hi>Parthia,</hi> or <hi>Germany</hi> had been ranſacked for their beſt Horſe of Manage.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Their thundring Hoofs did beat the trembling Ground,</l>
                  <l>Their luſty Neighing, made the Air reſound;</l>
                  <l>In Line moſt regular, they Marcht, to ſhow</l>
                  <l>That they by Rule, would Vanquiſh puiſſant Foe.</l>
                  <l>Such Courage, Ancient <hi>Sparta</hi> rarely bred,</l>
                  <l>Enough to make Great <hi>Homer's</hi> Heroes dread.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Never did Chieftain with more bravery Grace the Front of his Officers, than our Mighty <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> lead his youthful Army to the Tryal of their Valours: All acknowledging him to be the moſt undoubted Captain that ever gave Law to the Sword of his Enemy.</p>
               <p>The firſt day, having in moſt Graceful Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paſſed the Conſines of <hi>Olinders</hi> Vally; they aſcended a mighty Hill, which brought them into a Plain, within five Leagues of the perfidious <hi>Lymas's</hi> Army. Here they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to reſt themſelves that night, and take ſuch meaſures as might the better fit them for an Attack the next morning: Wherefore
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59471:32"/> the Riders diſmounting, encloſed a large piece of Campaign Ground, in the midſt of which they turned their Horſes to Graſs, that they might be the ſitter for the next days Travel. Whilſt our Famous <hi>Patrick,</hi> the brave <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus,</hi> and ſome chief of the young Nobles, adviſed which way they might give notice to the Caſtle of the fair <hi>Climena</hi> of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement towards her relief; but to their great Aſtoniſhment they were ſoon anſwered by the wonder of his Age, St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> who aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, that by the Vertue of his Sword, any one might paſs Incognito to the Caſtle, and bring them an account before the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Whereupon it was reſolved, that the Noble <hi>Olindarus</hi> ſhould (by the Meſſenger) give his Couſin a Letter of their deſign, which he immediately writ, in this ſort.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the thrice Fair <hi>Climena, Olindarus</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth greeting.</head>
                     <p>WHen theſe ſhall kiſs your fair hands, you may underſtand that my ſelf, and about Eight Hundred of the Principal youth of my Fathers Country, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unworthy deſigns of the Traytor <hi>Lymas</hi> againſt your Perſon, are now upon our March, in fifteen Leagues of your Caſtle; having for our Captain the moſt Renowned
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59471:32"/> St. <hi>Patrick</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whom ſome good Star brought to my Fathers Houſe, that very Night that we were muſtering our ſelves for this Expedition: He is a Perſon by unerring Fate deſigned to make all that he oppoſes Trophies to his Valour. We only wait an Anſwer from you by this Meſſenger, that we may know in the beſt manner how to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to your Service,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Olindarus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>No ſooner was this Letter written and ſealed, but St. <hi>Patrick</hi> laying his Enchanted Sword on the ſhoulder of the Page, and pronouncing the words, <hi>Preſto Remigrare;</hi> the Meſſenger Immediatly vaniſhed like a Bird through the Air, and in few minutes was at the beſieged Caſtle, paſſing over the Camp of <hi>Lymas,</hi> as if he had been the Foot-boy of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whileſt his Magical diſguiſe kept him unobſerved by the Souldiers and Watches; and not diſcovering himſelf until he came into the preſence of the Beautious <hi>Clymena:</hi> where we will leave him to receive his diſpatch, and return a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to St. <hi>Patrick</hi> and his Noble Brigade, whom we left on the Plaine before-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59471:33"/>
               <p>The Champaign where theſe Warlike Horſes were graſing was without any water, ſo that they had little ſtomach to fall to their green Salet without drink, being very Thirſty with their Travail; wherefore like generous Praun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers they carvetted round their paſture, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Soil with indignation that afforded them nor water to aſſwage their Martial heat. The Famous Horſe of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Champion pawing on the dry ground with great diſdain, ſuddainly there aroſe under his foot a large Fountain, from whence Iſſued ſuch abundance of Water, as ſerved not only for the Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Horſes, but their Riders, to the great Aſtoniſhment of all preſent: And no Wonder,
<q>
                     <l>For if there were ſuch Vertue in the Beaſt,</l>
                     <l>What muſt He have by whom he was Poſſeſt.</l>
                  </q> And preſently after, to increaſe their Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there ſell amongſt the Horſes ſo great a ſhowre of <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Beans,</hi> that the Cattle were Knee deep in Provender, where they wanton'd it with great Luxury, until the Trumpets the next morning ſounded to Horſe: And tho this Relation may pusſle the belief of a Heretical Reader, yet we may account it but a Puiſnie Miracle, if compared with thoſe more Stupendious Succeſſes that often atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59471:33"/> our Champion in his Heroick Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt the Noble <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and his brave Companions were with much wonder Contemplating on what had happened; the Page returned from the Caſtle of the Lady <hi>Clymena,</hi> and brought the following Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Clymena</hi> to the Noble <hi>Olindarus</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Health.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Right Noble and Dear Couſin,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOurs by your truſty Page came ſafe to our hand, with no leſs Welcom than the gentle ſhowers to the parched Earth; and we cannot but pay our beſt thanks to your Self, and thoſe Honourable Worthies with you, that with ſo much Gallantry have enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in defence of our Innocence againſt the Barbarous Violence of the Inhuman <hi>Lymas:</hi> eſpecially to that Mighty and Renowned <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> whom Fame ſpeaks more than Man, and from whoſe unconquerable Arm we may juſtly hope a happy Deliverance. We muſt now lay aſide all thoughts of beating of the Tyrant by an Army, for not half an hour before the arrival of your Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a Trumpeter from the Camp brought us this Challenge.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59471:34"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Philadon,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SInce thy boldneſs offereth to withold <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> from me; know that to Chaſtiſe thy folly, I have in my Camp a Gyant and Champion, who perſonally is reſolved to defy Thee, or whom thou ſhalt Appoint; if therefore either thy ſelf or any other ſhall be ſo hardy as to meet him Armed to morrow in the Plain, before the Caſtle, at the Hour of Two in the Afternoon, thou wilt there receive a juſt reward for thy preſumption.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Upon reading this Paper, my dear</hi> Philadon <hi>reſolved himſelf to Fight the mighty Gyant; but what apprehenſions that muſt needs put me into, you may eaſily imagine: I was reſolved rather to hazard all by a Sally, then permit it: But this I durſt not reveal to the Noble</hi> Philadon, <hi>whoſe great Soul believes all things ſuperable by the love of his poor</hi> Clymena. <hi>I leave the conduct of all to your more Judicious Council, expecting to hear from you in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Clymena.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter being read in the preſence of the Great and Mighty Champion St. <hi>Patrick,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59471:34"/> he immediately concluded the Gyant to be a Butt proper for him to ſhoot the Arrows of his high Courage at; and therefore reſolveth, before Day to be upon his March to ſo brave an Enterpriſe, by no means brooking any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay; wherefore ordering the Trumpets to give the Summons at that time; they laid down to take what refreſhment they could in the interim.</p>
               <p>About three in the Morning, the Trumpets according to Order giving the Signal, they were ſoon mounted, their Youthful Rage boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in hope of a ſuddain Encounter; their Furious Horſes (though on a very ſwift March) went Chaſing with Foam, as if their Riders made not haſt enough to the Fatal Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. By break of day they were come in view of <hi>Lymas's</hi> Camp, which ſoon took an Alarm at their unexpected approach, and were quickly in a poſture of defence: But the Gyant (having ſwallow'd a Calf and two Sheep for his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and drank a Firkin of Brandy as a Health to <hi>Lymas,</hi> and his next dayes ſucceſs) was in ſo profound a ſleep, that all the Cannon in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet could not have awakned him; but before his Eyes were unglued, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> had levell'd a forlorn of about Sixty of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, and ſtruck ſuch a Terrour into the reſt, as made them give him way to enter the Caſtle with his Troops, which he eaſily
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59471:35"/> did; for at the firſt hearing the Alarm, <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> concluded her generous Relievers were come, and was quickly confirmed in that her Opinion; for looking towards the Camp ſhe ſoon knew her Couſin <hi>Olindarus</hi> by his Horſe, and a White Feather in his Helmet, which had been her Brothers; wherefore cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Caſtle Eates to be opened, they found a ſpeedy entrance, none of <hi>Lymas's</hi> Men dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow them to the Outworks.</p>
               <p>As this unexpected Relief miniſtred much occaſion of joy to the Beſieged; who apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Gods had fought for them, and on ſo Extraordinary an Attempt received the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Encouragement Imaginable: So was it of as ill Conſequence to the Beſiegers; who now perceived they had to do with Perſons of ſuch Incomparable Gallantry and Courage, as dreaded not the dangers, nor Terrours ariſing to Cowards on ſuch occaſions; but rather with greateſt Reſolution courted Honour in the greateſt Difficulties. This made the Crafty <hi>Lymas</hi> (more then ever) rely on the force of his Monſtrous Gyant, in whom alone he now reſted his hope of Victory.</p>
               <p>Nor may it ſeem ſtrange, if on the alone Conſideration of this Mighty Monſter, <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> might think himſelf in Condition to Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the whole World: for he was of ſo vaſt a ſtature, that the Stouteſt Man on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59471:35"/> could ſcarcely reach up to his Navel; and (if Fame be not a Lyar) he was Grandſier to the King of <hi>Bombaza</hi> named <hi>Bahadercam,</hi> whoſe fall ſo ſignalized the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lour of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Jones.</hi> This Gyant was named <hi>Camba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor,</hi> born on the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains, and was from his Infancy bred up in the hardſhips of that Climate, abounding with bitter Froſts, and Snows; and in the Company of Lyons, Bears and Tygres; out of whoſe Iaws (when a Boy) he reſcued many a Breakfaſt: He would as ordinaryly fell a Lyon with a Stroak of his Fiſt on the Pole, as a Warren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner kills Cunnies. He was ſo great an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Flocks of the Neighbour Villages, that he had deſtroyed moſt of them; and ſent their owners into the other World for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to protect them from his devouring Chapps. He would take the maddeſt Bull by the Hornes, and twiſt his head off.</p>
               <p>One day being drawn down to the Sea ſide, he eſpied a Mighty Whale not far from the ſhore, which he thought might make a proper Booty for his greatneſs, wherefore caſting a mighty Oak into the Sea, he beſtrid it in purſuit of the Scaly Monſter; and the Wind taking hold of the boughs of the Tree, drave him aſhore on that Coaſt where <hi>Lymas</hi> had raiſed his Army againſt the chaſte <hi>Clymena.</hi> At his firſt landing, ſpying a Company of Men, he
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59471:36"/> deſigned immediately to Sacrifice them to the Appeaſment of his all-devouring Gorge, which was then more than ordinary whetted by the ſharpneſs of the Sea-Air: But they (ſoon perceiving the purpoſe of the Fell Monſter) left the place, and reſigned him the proſpect of a Flock of Sheep, which at that time ſerved him for a Supper.</p>
               <p>His Mouth was ſo large, that it ſeemed like a Percullis, with five ſets of Teeth, of that ſtrength as would bite in ſunder Barrs of Iron: The firſt bitt he made at Sheep, Staggs, or Bullocks, was at their Horns; which he preſently ſnapt off, and ſpit out of his Mouth for fear of choaking; the reſt of the body was ſoon diſpatched down his throat, into the unſatiable fornace of his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
               <p>Now the Baſe-minded <hi>Lymas</hi> hearing of this Inhuman Monſter, bribed him (with whole Heards of Cattle, and Flocks of Sheep, beſides Tunns of Liquors) to put him in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Incomparable <hi>Clymena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But no ſooner was the ever Famous St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> with the reſt of his Brigade, got into the Caſtle; (after having been Complimented by the Fair <hi>Clymena,</hi> and her lovely <hi>Philadon,</hi> for the great Honour they did them in attempting ſuch hazardous Adventures for their ſakes: and having on their parts declared their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59471:36"/> to hazzard their lives in purſuit of ſo glorious an Vndertaking:) but they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agreed to ſend <hi>Lymas</hi> this Anſwer to his Challenge.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthyeſt of Men, <hi>Lymas; Philadon</hi> ſendeth Greeting.</head>
                     <p>THy Challenge by the Trumpet the laſt even, was received; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thereto, Know thy Champion ſhall at the Time and Place be met by a Friend of Mine, who, for all Thy Bravadoes ſhall ſend his filthy Soul to the Shades of <hi>Acharon:</hi> And as for Thee, if thou dareſt to be his Second, I will my Self undertake with equal Weapon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide thy Pretentions to my Faireſt <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Philadon.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>drummer relaying the message to Lymas</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>No ſooner was the Meſſenger returned, but the Gallant <hi>Philadon</hi> began to ſet all things in Order for this Mighty Combat, there were Galleries Erected for <hi>Clymena,</hi> and the Ladies with her on the outſide of the Caſtle, againſt the plain ground; from whence they might be Spectators of the Bloody Encounter; The
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59471:37"/> Noble <hi>Philadon,</hi> with the brave <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and the reſt of the Gallant Horſe that were in the Caſtle, drew out before the entrance of the Garriſon, whilſt the Infantry placed themſelves on the Walls: On the other ſide, <hi>Lymas</hi> had drawn his Men in a Line, making as it were a boundary to the other ſide of the Plain; ſo that the middle ſpace between the two Armies, was the Field where the ever Famous <hi>Patrick</hi> was to ſignalize his immortal Proweſs by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the dreadfulleſt Gyant that ever was mentioned in Romantick Author: Whileſt the Souldiers on each ſide were in readineſs to have engaged, if any foul play ſhould be uſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59471:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The Dreadful Combat betwixt St. <hi>Patrick</hi> and the Monſtrous Gyant <hi>Cambagor.</hi> His Voyage by Sea towards the Coaſt of <hi>Greece,</hi> and the ſtrange Adventures that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him in that Voyage.</head>
               <p>NOw the appointed hour being come, wherein the Fortunes of the Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Clymena</hi> were to be determined by the matchleſs Sword of the invincible St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> he marched out of the Caſtle to the Plain before mentioned, attended by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of the Nobility moſt ſplendidly Accoutred, with ſuch gayity of Plumes, Embroideries, Paintings, Guildings; as if they had been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Nuptials of ſome Magnificent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; the very Aire receiving Luſtre from the dazeling ſplendour of their Armes and Trappings; and the Vally reſounded with the Eccho of their Silver Trumpets. They found the Monſtrous <hi>Cambagor</hi> already entred the Liſts, (he being the Challenger) his very appearance ſtruck a terrible apprehenſion into moſt of the Spctators, by the dreadful gaſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his grim Countenance; his heighth was about thirty foot, ſo that thoſe that had not lived in an Age of Gyants, would have took
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59471:38"/> him for a walking Steeple; for compared to him the Monſters in the <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> would have ſeemed to be but Pigmie-Pages: His Shield was the Hull of a Ship, his Spear a mighty Maſt, pointed at the Top with half a Tun of Iron; at his back was hung a Club, being the Body of a mighty Oak; for any thing leſs ponderous ſeemed but as a feather in his hand. Our glorious Champion St. <hi>Patrick</hi> was mounted on his own truſty Courſor, and Armed at all points as was before deſcribed, with that Enchanted Armour found in the Magical Cave, which no force of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon could penetrate; and though for Stature of Body he came very ſhort of the Over-grown Gyant, yet he far exceeded him in Courage; and was not much inferiour to him for ſtrength of Body, which joined to the greatneſs of his Valour, made large amends for the diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Stature.</p>
               <p>Having view'd his Monſtrous Antagoniſt, the ever-Famous <hi>Patrick</hi> rid gently to him, and denouncing a generous and brave Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he alighted from off his Horſe, counting it diſhonourable for ſo great a Champion to Fight even a Monſtrous Gyant at ſuch diſadvantage: So taking his Target and Spear, he began the moſt Tremendous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59471:39"/> that ever was related, there having never been ſo glorious a Victory obtained at ſo vaſt a diſadvantage.</p>
               <p>The Gyant with Prodigious force made a blow with his mighty Spear at the Head of St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> which he nimbly avoiding, with a ſuddain thruſt of his Lance, gave the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a wound in the right Knee; the horned point of it ſticking ſo faſt in the Ioynt, that our Champion was fain to jerk with all his ſtrength to recover it again; at that, the Fell Gyant fetching another blow at his Head, enough to have battered a Rock; St. <hi>Patrick</hi> with his Target caſt it off on his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the weight of it ſending him to the ground; but falling only on his Breech, he roſe with ſuch nimble advantage, that his Spear found way through the keel of the Gyants Shield to wound him in the Arm; <hi>Cambagor's</hi> Spear breaking with the laſt ſtroke he made on St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Shoulder: And finding his Shield not Proof againſt the Irreſiſtable force of his Weapon, he caſt it down with ſuch Violence, that it brake in pieces on the ground; then betaking himſelf to his mighty Club, he laid about him with ſuch fury, as muſt ſoon have daſht our Champion to Attoms, had not the Excellence
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59471:39"/> of his Armor, and the wonderful ſtrength of his Conſtitution preſerved him. This En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter continued long, and to the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment of all the Spectators, who were ſtruck, with wonder to ſee a Man of Ordinary Size and Proportion reſiſt, and overcome the Violence of ſuch a mighty Monſter.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>St. Patrick, after beheading the Giant Cambagor</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Thus fell this Terrible and Formidable Gyant <hi>Cambagor</hi> by the hand of that wonder of the World, the Mighty <hi>Patrick,</hi> who (had he lived) would in ſhort time have devoured the Cattle of a Kingdom: The which Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Action filled the Air with the loud Shouts and Acclamations of all about the Caſtle, whilſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59471:40"/> the Camp of <hi>Lymas</hi> were in great Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for the loſs of their (as they thought) <hi>Invincible Champion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the ſight hereof, the Princely <hi>Philadon</hi> advanced, to purſue the Noble Victory by revenging his wrongs upon the Perſon of the Trayterous <hi>Lymas:</hi> who was ſo far from appearing as Second to his boaſted Champion, that on ſlght of his Fall, he withdrew into the Rear of his Army, and ſuddainly rid out of the Field; whilſt the Noble <hi>Philadon</hi> with great honour demanded him to make good his Challenge: But he not being to be found by the Officers of his Army; and they having advice from the Rear, that he had quitted the Field, immediately broke their Commiſſions; acknowledging to the Generous <hi>Philadon</hi> the Injuſtice of their Quarrel; and taking an Oath never more to appear in ſo unworthy a Cauſe; they forthwith diſmiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Souldiers, who were weary of ſerving ſo bad a Maſter; and diſperſt themſelves to their reſpective Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations. Some of <hi>Lymas's</hi> Neighbours taking the Road that lead to his Country, eſpyed him in a Field about a Mile diſtant from the Camp; where he had turned Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner to himſelf, and with his own hands had hanged himſelf to a Tree near the way ſide: this Spectacle much Confirmed them in their Opinions of the baſeneſs of his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59471:41"/> whilſt they there ſaw him tyed up to the Deſtiny uſually attending Cowards in Deſpair. Where we will leave him expoſed to the Eternal Infamy and Terrour of ſuch Barbarous and Inhuman Villains; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again to the Caſtle, which now reſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with nothing but the High praiſes of the Invincible St. <hi>Patrick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They divided the Body of the Gyant into four Quarters, which were ſent to four Principal Cities of the Realm, to be fixed on the Gates in Memory of ſo famous an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit; the Head was carried into the Caſtle, and faſtned on a Pole over the Gate of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance: St. <hi>Patrick</hi> having only taken a Lock of his Beard, which he ever after wore faſtned to his Plume on the Creſt of his Helmet, as a Trophie of his unmatcht Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and undoubted Proweſs.</p>
               <p>Thus by the Courage of this Puiſſant <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> was the Fair <hi>Clymena</hi> delivered from the Cruel Seige of the moſt Infamous <hi>Lymas,</hi> the Noble <hi>Philadon</hi> rid of his unworthy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and the whole World freed from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Salvage <hi>Cambagor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Night was ſpent in all the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of Rejoycing, the ſtraightneſs of the time would afford, by fiering of Guns, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Bonfiers, and Martial Conſorts of their Drums and Trumpets; whilſt the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59471:41"/> Princely <hi>Clymena,</hi> with a Noble Trayn of Beautious Ladyes came to kiſs the hand of her great Benefactor: The Courteous <hi>Philadon,</hi> the brave <hi>Olindarus,</hi> with the reſt of the Young Lords, ſtriving which ſhould exceed the other in paſſing the higheſt Complements and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums on ſo unparalleld an Adventure: The Incomparable St. <hi>Patrick</hi> with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Gallantry Imaginable returned their high Careſſes with this Generous Anſwer:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That all that had been done, and what ever elſe lay in his Power to perform, was but too little to ſhew the great Service he had for Perſons of their Extraordinary Figure, and high Perfections. Adding, that what had happened, muſt rather be imputed to the influence of</hi> Clymena's <hi>Stars, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Juſtice of her Cauſe; ſo that it was Impoſſible an Action ſo glorious could fail of Succeſs, tho attempted by a weaker hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, whileſt theſe great <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> were entertertaining the Champion with theſe Rhetorical Harangues; the Servants of <hi>Clymena</hi> had made proviſion of a Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſupper, not unſuitable to the Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narineſs of the Occaſion. The Nobles and Ladyes ſitting down in the Hall, were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59471:42"/> with all the Choice Variety the greateſt Pallace could Boaſt of; They teſtified their hearty Congratulation of that Dayes Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by plentiful Glaſſes of rich Wine, with which the Table abounded; whilſt a Muſical Conſort of Harps and Viols feaſted their Ears with this</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>SONG.</head>
                           <l>NOw, now the Fight's done, and the great God of War,</l>
                           <l>Lies Sleeping in Shades, and unrifles his Care;</l>
                           <l>Love Laughs at his Reſt,</l>
                           <l>Whileſt the Souldier Alarms;</l>
                           <l>And with Drums and with Trumpets</l>
                           <l>They Beat up to Arms;</l>
                           <l>He rides on his Lance, and the Buſhes he bangs,</l>
                           <l>And his broad Bloody Sword on a Willow Tree hangs.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Song ended; the Spatious Hall rung with another Conſort, which was of Huzza's, whilſt a Health was drank round to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Patrick</hi> Champion of <hi>Ireland;</hi> which he requited by beginning another to the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitable and Noble Lord <hi>Olindor,</hi> Father of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59471:42"/> 
                  <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and Vnkle to <hi>Clymena;</hi> and ſo in Order, till a Glaſs had been pledged to every particular Perſons health at that Noble Table. Nor were the Common Souldiers without a large ſhare of the Bountious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of that Night; for many Veſſels of Wine, and other Excellent Liquors were placed in the Court amongſt them; with a great plenty of Beef, Veniſon, Lamb, and other Extraordinary Proviſion, anſwerable to the Grandure of the Lady of that Manſion: ſo that a Vniverſal Ioy diffuſed it ſelf through the whole Caſtle, and was Legible in every face; and every Tongue thought it ſelf not well Employed, that ſounded not the High Praiſes of the moſt Famous St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> whoſe inſuperable Courage, brave Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and ſtupendious Succeſs, was now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Diſcourſe and Wonder of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>This was that night (wherein the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded <hi>Lymas</hi> deſigned to have wantoned in the Ruine of <hi>Clymena's</hi> Honour; to have Tryumphed in the Overthrow of <hi>Philadon,</hi> and have made himſelf Lord of that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Caſtle) turned into a <hi>Jubilee</hi> for the defeat of the wretched <hi>Lymas;</hi> the ſlaughter of the barbarous <hi>Cambagor,</hi> and the mighty delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Phyladon,</hi> and <hi>Clymena.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59471:43"/>
               <p>They ſpent their time in Vnwearied Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes, and Brisk Entertainments, until <hi>Chanticlere</hi> had ſummoned the Morning to open the Portals of the Eaſt: when by Vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Conſent, all addreſſed themſelves to make Truce with <hi>Morpheus</hi> for the repoſe of ſome Hours, to fit them the better for the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Following day. Therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting the renowned St. <hi>Patrick</hi> to a moſt Princely Apartment appointed for him, they left him to reflect on the Tranſactions of that day, and to thank his Stars for their happy influence.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as the brave <hi>Olindarus</hi> awaked the next Morning, he might perceive the Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed Chariot of <hi>Apollow,</hi> had aſcended the <hi>Olympick</hi> Hill, almoſt Six hours Iourney; when (willing that the Youth, which in cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous manner had attended him, ſhould no longer be kept from their doubtful Relations; and deſirous to carry home the glad Tydings of this Glorious Victory, to the concerned <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lindor</hi>) he gave his Trumpets Order to give the Signal, that his Company ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to Horſe; ſo that by that time they were ready, he with his young Nobles, had taken their leaves of the Generous <hi>Philadon,</hi> and the lovely <hi>Clymena,</hi> and attended the Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Worlds Wonder, St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> where kiſſing his hand, and receiving of him
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59471:43"/> many Teſtimonies of the great Opinion he had of them, highly applauding them for their Gallantry, in offering themſelves on that Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion in the ſervice of the excellent <hi>Clymena:</hi> Embracing the Princely Youth <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and by him ſending the moſt grateful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments imaginable to his Noble Hoſt <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor;</hi> they parted: St. <hi>Patrick</hi> accompanying them to the outer Gate of the Caſtle, and ſome of the Principal of the Gentlemen at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending them ſome Miles on their march.</p>
               <p>Never was the Loud Trump of Fame ſet in Work, on a more Wonderful Occaſion, than this great Overthrow of the Dreadful <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bagor;</hi> ſhe had almoſt burſt her ſwolne Cheeks with making the ſound rattle through the <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin:</hi> So that now all the Admirers of Great and Heroick Acts, bent their Courſe to <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena's</hi> Caſtle to pay their Homage to the more than Humane St. <hi>Patrick;</hi> whom they had much ado to forbear Adoring: Many Statues were Erected in memory of this Famous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit, and the mighty Champions in Forraign Parts, ſtood Amazed at the report of ſo Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous an Adventure. But notwithſtanding, our Worthy Knight were dayly wayted on, and Congratulated by the greateſt Lords of the Country, and treated with a profuſion of Dainties, beſitting the Grandure of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Monarch: yet did none of theſe Charming
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59471:44"/> Entertainments reliſh with our Martial <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe,</hi> whoſe great Courage could not ſtoop to the ſoft Pleaſures of an Eaſie and Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Life; but putting on a reſolution to give a taſte of his Extraordinary Valour to remoter parts of the World, and to ſignalize his Proweſs where-ever Fame. had a Regiſter to Record it; he went to the lovely pair <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladon</hi> and <hi>Clymena,</hi> ſignifying to them his Determination ſpeedily to depart in queſt of farther Honour, and to add new Trophies to his Mighty Courage.</p>
               <p>The Fair Lovers heard their Mighty Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian with no ſmall trouble, conſidering they were now like to part with the Defendant of their Lives, the Cheriſher of their Loves, and Family, and the undoubted glory of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Race; but however ſubmitting to his Reſolution, they only requeſted him as he had been the happy Champion of their Affections; and had thereby enroled his own Name in the Temple of <hi>Mars;</hi> he would pleaſe to continue a few Dayes to ſee Theirs entred in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Hymen:</hi> and as by his Stupendious Valour he had preſerved the Beauteous <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> for her <hi>Philadon,</hi> he would afford them the farther Honour to ſee them Ratifie their mutual Vows, by performing the Sacred Rights. The moſt Complaiſant <hi>Heroe</hi> grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their requeſt, and in the mean time put all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59471:44"/> things in readineſs for his Voyage; He hired a Ship in an adjoyning Port, and furniſhed it with <hi>Mariners;</hi> and all conveniencies of Victuals and other Neceſſaries; he ſent alſo his Magical Armour on board, and fitted a place for his truſty Steed <hi>Crapearo</hi> (for that was his Name, as Authors notifie) likewiſe he ſent on board divers Cheſts, and Trunks fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Extraordinary rarities to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Value, that had been preſented him by the grateful <hi>Clymena,</hi> and her beloved <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt the Renowned <hi>Patrick</hi> was thus fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all things for his Voyage, the two Lovers had prepared themſelves for the long-wiſht for Nuptials; the glad Morning was come; the fair Bride was awaked with an Excellent noiſe of Wind-Muſick, the Hymeneal Lamps were Kindled, the Virgins were ready, the Prieſt attended, whilſt the Altar of the lofty Temple perfumed its ſtately Roof with Clouds of Sacred Incence. All things being ready, they proceeded in this Order.</p>
               <p>Firſt went twenty four Damſels in white Satten playing on Pipes, and Timbrils after the Antient manner, then twelve beautiful Boyes about twelve years of age, carrying large Candles burning of pureſt Virgin War, they were habited in Cloath of Silver, with Starves of Pink-Colour Silk; after them the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59471:45"/> Prieſt in his Miter, and Pontificallibus for that Occaſion; then was the Bride Conducted by the Noble young <hi>Olindarus,</hi> and another Noble Man of Principal Quality; her Gown was of Pearl-Coloured Sattin, wrought with True-loves-knots, and Flowers of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; over all, a large Veil of the fineſt Tif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fany: The young Lords were in Veſts of Green Silk, richly ſaid with Gold lace, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing white Beavors, with Curious plumes of Snow-white Feathers, tipt with Pink-colour. After her, followed a fair train of Young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Principal Quality, in dreſſes Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary rich, wherein the skill of the beſt-famed Taylers had been Employed, being attended with many little Pages in very proper Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, each wearing according to the Device and Phancy of his Miſtreſs. After theſe, came the Princely Bridegroom in a veſt of Sky-coloured Sattin curiouſly Embroidered with Silver and Pearl; having on his Breaſt a Golden Harp ſet with Diamonds, after the Order of St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> who had beſtowed that on him as a Badge in Memory of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Champion that ſlew the Gyant; on one ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he had caſt a Pearl-coloured Mantle wrought with hearts, and Roſes of Gold: he was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by two Beautiful Maidens of Noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, in Veſtures of Lemon-colour, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Silk, made ſomwhat ſhort, that their
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59471:45"/> Satten Buskens might appear, which were of Carnation Satten Embroidered, and ſet with Silver Bells: On their Heads they had <hi>Tyara's</hi> of Feathers, of Skie, White, and Pink-colour: after them came the Noble Old Lord <hi>Olindor,</hi> Vnkle to the Bride, and on his Right hand the Moſt Renowned Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> being followed by a very Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Company of Young Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of principal Quality: Divers Chariots and Coaches attended, wherein after the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony was performed, this Princely Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny placed themſelves; and in great Pomp and Admirable Order returned to the Caſtle, which from this time we muſt call <hi>Philadons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing imaginable was Omitted, that might expreſs the Bounty of the Bridegroom, and his Bride, or the high Welcom of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gueſts. The Bells rung at the Temple, the Trumpets Ecchoed on the Caſtle walls, the Hall reſounded with Muſical Inſtruments; and after the Second Courſe had been ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Table, this Song was Sung to a well-tuned Conſort of Lutes, in praiſe of the Fair Bride.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <pb n="84" facs="tcp:59471:46"/>
                           <head>SONG.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>HAil to the Mirtle Shades,</l>
                              <l>All Hail to the Nimphs of the Field,</l>
                              <l>Kings cannot here invade,</l>
                              <l>Nor Virtue her Freedom yeild;</l>
                              <l>Beauty now opens her Arms,</l>
                              <l>To ſoften her Languiſhing mind,</l>
                              <l>And <hi>Phillis</hi> unlocks her Charmes,</l>
                              <l>Ah! <hi>Phillis,</hi> Ah! why ſo kind?</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> the Soul of Love,</l>
                              <l>The Joy of the Neighbouring Swains,</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> that Crowns the Grove,</l>
                              <l>And <hi>Phillis</hi> that guilds the Plains;</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> that ne'er had the Skill</l>
                              <l>To Paint, or to Patch, or be Fine,</l>
                              <l>Yet <hi>Phillis</hi> whoſe Eyes can kill,</l>
                              <l>Whom Nature had made Divine.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> whoſe Charming Tongue</l>
                              <l>Makes Labour, and Pain a delight;</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> that makes the day Young,</l>
                              <l>And ſhortens the Live-long Night;</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Phillis</hi> whoſe Lips like May</l>
                              <l>Still laugh at the ſweets that they bring,</l>
                              <l>Where Beauty knows no decay,</l>
                              <l>But Sits with Eternal Spring.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:59471:46"/>
               <p>Whilſt their Ears were thus delighted with divers ſorts of Excellent Muſick, plentiful Healths of Noble Wine went round the Table, after that of the new-made Husband and Wife; a large Brimmer was Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Health of their ever Famous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron and Champion the Heroick St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> accompanied with loud Acclamations in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of his Memorable Adventure in the Deſtruction of the Monſter <hi>Cambagor.</hi> Thus with Dances and other Diverſions ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Occaſion, they ſpent the Night; whilſt the Noble <hi>Philadon,</hi> and beautious <hi>Clymena</hi> withdrew to their Bridal Chamber, there to taſte thoſe more refined delights that were to Crown that Feſtival. The reſt of the Company, as they ſaw occaſion, retiring to their reſpective Dormitories.</p>
               <p>No ſooner had the Glorious Charioter of the Spheres the next Morning with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulgent beams guilded the tops of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and opened a moſt pleaſant proſpect over the Fertil Plains; but our St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> the true Mirrour of brave Chivalry left the ſoft repoſe of his downy Pillow; and tyred with the un-ſouldierly delights of an Idle Luxury; his Martial Soul ſet forward in purſuit of thoſe Noble Glories, that muſt give a farther Honour to his Renowned Shield, and ſet the Pupils of <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> on
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59471:47"/> work, to erect Collums to his high Praiſes. So that he preſently gave order to his Page to fit his Horſe with a ſuit of Extraordinary rich Furniture that had been preſented him (amongſt many other Rarities) by <hi>Clymena;</hi> he had on a ſtately Coat of Male, a Coſſet &amp; Beavor of Gold, with a large Milk-white Plume, having tyed to it the lock of <hi>Camba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gors</hi> Beard, a Scarf of Carnation Saſſnet; whereon, by the Art of a curious Needle, were lively Expreſſed Gyants heads Embelliſhed with Gold: This was likewiſe preſented by the Noble Bride; for as we told you before, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> had ſent his Enchanted Armour, with other Curioſities on board his Ship. Being thus Equipped, he came to bid farewel to the Gallant Bridegroom; and Beautious Bride, who had dreſſed themſelves ſooner than ordinary that Morning to take their Leave of our Famous Champion; the Old Lord <hi>Olindor,</hi> and his Son the brave <hi>Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus</hi> were likewiſe ready to pay their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpects to him: So that coming all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into the Hall, they there paſſed ſuch mutual Compliments, as were agreeable to ſuch a Seaſon: Then the Princely <hi>Hero</hi> departed in order to take his Horſe, but that was prevented by the ever Courteous <hi>Olindor</hi> who had ordered his Chariot to be ready that he might accompany the Admired <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:59471:47"/> on his was to the Port, all the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants waited on him to the Gate, and <hi>Philadon</hi> &amp; <hi>Clymena</hi> had likewiſe their Chariot ready to have born him Company, but he would by no means permit it; ſo that compelling them to tarry behind, they there took their laſt leave of him; only the Young <hi>Olindarus</hi> accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied his Aged Father, who having placed our Champion at his right hand, made his Man drive until he had brought St. <hi>Patrick</hi> over a Bridge five Miles on his way; where alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they embraced, and gave each other the moſt hearty Teſtimonies of an Inviolable Friendſhip; Here our Matchleſs Knight Mounting his own Horſe (which had been led by his Page) took his direct way to the Port, whileſt the Noble <hi>Olindor</hi> and his Son re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Caſtle of <hi>Philadon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Early in the Evening they arrived at the Port, and preſently went on Board; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wind favourable, forthwith hoiſted Sail for the Coaſt of <hi>Greece,</hi> where we muſt now trace our Famous <hi>Patrick</hi> doing ſuch wonders as would puſle any but a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick</hi> Faith. <hi>Neptune</hi> had now with his Trident ſmoothed the tangled Curles of Thetis Billows, the ſurface of the Deep had put on ſuch an even level, as might invite the <hi>Halcion</hi> to build; her Mountainous Waves were ſo depreſſed, as if the Watry
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59471:48"/> God had paved a way over her Rugged Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel for the Veſſel of ſo great a Champion to paſs ſmoothly on; the Sturgeons, Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins, with other the Scally Inhabitants, danced and played about the Ship; as being glad a Knight, the wonder of the Land, ſhould Honour their Element with his Renowned burthen: The ſurly Emperour of the Eolean Cave had likewiſe muſled his Roaring Bluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo that there ſeemed to be an Amicable trute between the Airy and the Watry Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions: Never was obtained ſuch a ſereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſince the enraged <hi>Neptune</hi> huſt the Loud-Tongued Troops from his Briny Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, when they aſſaulted the <hi>Trojan</hi> Cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p>But as uſually, the greateſt Succeſſes are attended with ſome Croſs and diſaſterous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; and the Shining <hi>Planet Phebus</hi> having performed his daily task, his reſplendent Rays, give place to the ſhades of Gloomy Darkneſs, and the ſad ſolitudes of the ſucceeding Night: So this Glorious Tranquility met with a Misfortune, not unuſually attending thoſe that Travel on the Vaſt Watery Deſart. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now paſſed ſeveral days in an undiſturbed Quietude, they at laſt met with a very ſtrange Adventure, which happened in this ſort.</p>
               <p>Paſſing by an Iſland remote from any Continent, a mighty <hi>Whale,</hi> the Gyant of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59471:48"/> the <hi>Ocean,</hi> met their Veſſel, which being of no great Bulk, and the Night ſuch, as they diſcerned not the approach of ſo Potent a Foe, ſuddenly putting her ſelf under one ſide of the Ship, Violently Overthrew it in the Sea; ſo that, but few of the men were ſaved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Famous <hi>Patrick,</hi> his Page <hi>Mac,</hi> and five others, who being not far from the ſhore, made a ſhift to get to the Iſland, where with much bitterneſs they endured the Wet and Cold of the Night, untill the next Morning; when caſting their Eyes to the place of the miſerable Wreck, they eſpyed the Overthrown Veſſel floating on the Water, and the huge <hi>Whale</hi> ſtill plying her ſelf about it; whereat, the Enraged Champion taking up a keen ſtone from the Sea ſide, Flang it with ſuch force at the Whale, that it cut a large wound through his ſide, whereat iſſued ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Blood as ſtained the Water a great wayes round the Place; the Beaſt finding her ſelf ſorely wounded (as the Nature of the Whale is) made to the Shore, and caſt her ſelf on the Sands not far from the place where St. <hi>Patrick</hi> was; where wanting Water to carry her off, ſhe in little time dyed for want of her own Element: Our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion and his Men dividing the Vaſt Body into divers parts, got it ſo far on Land, as was beyond the power of the Sea to fetch
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59471:49"/> her off again. Amidſt the Horrour of their preſent Diſaſter, it was a little relief to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the Fatal work of their overthrow ſhould ſo ſoon, and by ſo ſtrange means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Puniſhment for the Irreparable injury. But what can reſiſt the hand of St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> when the Monſters of the Land and Sea, fall before his Mighty Puiſſance?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. How St. <hi>Patrick</hi> recovered his Veſſel, the Miracle of his Horſe <hi>Crapearo,</hi> and what happened in the farther proſecution of his Voyage to <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHilſt our Ship-wrackt Paſſengers were in great thoughtfulneſs how they ſhould get off the Iſland, and proſecute the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned Voyage; there being on the place, no Inhabitant, nor any Convenience that could give them any hope of a ſuppply for their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; whilſt ſome of them even wiſht they had been drowned with their Fellows, for fear of the miſeries they were like farther to ſuffer: Our matchleſs <hi>Hero,</hi> both by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his admirable Patience, and the great bravery of his Courageous ſpeeches, ſo heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, that it ſeemed, as if he had convey'd
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59471:49"/> a new Soul into their Bodyes; ſuch Vertues doth the very preſence of a Valiant man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, even into very Cow-heads; but he that never knew what it was to fear, thought it could be of no uſe to him now; beſides, it would argue a great Puſilanimity of Soul, which would ill become a Perſon cut out to be famous to all Poſterity. Whilſt therefore he was ſweetning his fellow ſufferers with the moſt Sugar'd Exhortations he could on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain invent, and in which (too) he was very dexterous; ſo the kind waves (relenting the loſs of ſo Famous a Champion had on their Element) threw the Wreck ſo near to the ſhoar, that they could lay hold on ſome of the Tackling; when our nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r-enough-Admired <hi>Patrick,</hi> ſetting both hands with all his might to the Stern, turned the Veſſel clear upon her Keel: But you muſt imagine, the falling back of the Water, helped much towards the effecting thereof: But Alas! if there had been no water at all, it could not have been impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to perform; with whom Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were as common, as for us to put on and off our Cloaths. The Seamen ſeeing this Wonder of his Sex, had again put them in a poſſibility of Saving themſelves, ſoon got upon the Deck, and looking into the Hold, they might there diſcern the None-ſuch <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearo</hi> ſtill alive: For you muſt know, that the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59471:50"/> 
                  <hi>Whale</hi> had caſt the Veſſel into ſuch a poſture, that the water could not get in, becauſe all the Hatches and Port-holes where the Air might get out, were ſtopped; and ſo the Ship remained like a woodden Bowl, reverſed on a Tub of Water, which becauſe the Air is pent in, keeps out the other Element; ſome of the Seamen too, which they thought had peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, were found alive under the Hatches, to the exceeding Comfort of St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> and the reſt of their Ships Company: But our poor <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearo</hi> was ſomewhat battered on his Cheek, Side, and Thigh, by the turning of the Veſſel; when St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> only ſmoothing his hand over it, it preſently grew whole, and Skin and Hair came on it in the ſame inſtant; ſo that there was no ſign of any hurt had been there.</p>
               <p>Then viewing the Trunks and Cheſts wherein the Noble Champions Rich Habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were packed, they found they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no damage at all; and though the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Sword had lain in the Water, yet ſuch was the Virtue of it, that it preſerved from Ruſt, and had no apparent injury: But yet one Principal Thing was miſſing; for the Victuals being ſtowed in one of the upper Decks, where the Hatches were open, they were all fallen out, and carryed away by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of the water, ſo that there was not ſo much as a <hi>Cheeſe,</hi> a diſh of <hi>Peaſe,</hi> a piece
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59471:50"/> of <hi>Beef</hi> or <hi>Pork</hi> left, only a Barrel of <hi>Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets</hi> remained, that had been ſtowed in the Purſers Cabin.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a wolf offering a newly slain sheep to St. Patrick</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Thus by the Aſſiſtance of this Famous Man, were the poor fainting Sea-men, once more in a proſpect of ſomewhat to aſſwage their Hunger; but now (as if Nature had made defects on purpoſe, that the Famous <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> might ſupply them,) there was not one ſtick of Wood to be found on the whole Iſland; ſo that unleſs they ſhould make a Fire of their Ships-Tackling, they could have nothing to Broil their Meat: Wherefore the Vigilant
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59471:51"/> Champion ſearching about, came at laſt to a Pond of Water, which was Frozen over by the extream Cold of the Seaſon: therefore ordering his Men to brake up the Ice, they fell to Work upon it; and as it broke, it ſplitted into gads and pieces, like Billets of Wood; whereat, the <hi>Hero</hi> laying ſome of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and rubbing them with the point of his Sword, they immediately took Fire, and burnt like ſtates of Deal, or Scotch-Coal; by which they ſoon Roaſted their Mutton, and Lamb, and Boyled ſeveral pieces of the Fiſh, out of which came ſuch abundance of Oyl, as ſerved them for Dripping and Sauce for their other Meat.</p>
               <p>The Servants of St. <hi>Patrick</hi> being Fed, and Repleniſhed, began now to conclude, that it was impoſſible for them to want any thing whileſt they were with ſuch a Maſter, that could make the Sea caſt him up Fiſh, the Wolves provide him Fleſh, and the Water to yield him Fire; ſo that now being revived with Victuals, and ſuch Conſiderations, they luſtily apply themſelves to fit their Veſſel for her farther Voyage, reſolving not to deſert ſo notable a Maſter, even in the moſt hazardous Adventures.</p>
               <p>In few days, by their great Induſtry, the Ship was again fitted for her Voyage; but then, not knowing, how long it might be before
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59471:52"/> they might come at a place to Victual, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet no farther ſupply, but what the Care, and Wondrous Fortune of St. <hi>Patrick</hi> daily provided for them, they therefore beſought him not to Adventure on an unknown Sea, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till there were ſome probability for their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence; adding, they might with leſs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Danger, continue on the Iſland, where they had found Food, than truſt the mercileſs Ocean, where it would be impoſſible for them to live, without a ſtore of Proviſion. But the Mirrour of Rnighthood, St. <hi>patrick,</hi> made them this Reply: <hi>That it would ill become the Gods, whoſe Champion he was, not to make proviſion for him, whilſt he was in purſuit of ſuch Glorious Atchievements as ſhould make Altars be reared to them; and their Temples reſound with the loud Praiſes of his mighty Chivalry: That they did very ill to diſtruſt the benignity of his Stars, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſo late proof of the great Succeſs which always attends <hi>Heroick</hi> minds, ſince even all the Elements Conſpire to ſerve them. That he had met with no oppoſition from productions purely vulgar, or in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon courſe of Nature; for they ſaw that even the moſt Salvage and Ravening Woolves (contrary to their Natural diſpoſition) Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to him: but the danger he had me withal, was only from Monſters, and thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:59471:52"/> Mightieſt Products of the Land, and Water; Both which notwithſtanding had paid their Lives a Tribute to his Knightly Valour. Then looking on them with a chearful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſomwhat raiſing his Voice. Courage</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my Mates; you ſhall ſee the never failing Fortune that attend Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So carrying on board that ſmall Portion of Food they had left, they with great reſolution Embarked, and put again to Sea; being In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the brave Expreſſions and high Courage of their Valiant Leader.</p>
               <p>But now the Croſs Fates had their Game to play, which they did to their utmoſt, all the Evil and Malignant Aſpects aſſiſting; to break (if poſſible) the Viſtorious ſucceſs of this Invincible Champion: For you muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Iſland they were under was Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate in a Climate under the Dominion of Evil Spirits, by which only it was Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: all the Familiars of the Famous Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Wizzards, Conjurers, and Witches had Reſort hither; here they kept their Rendezuous and general Councils; to which many times they invited thoſe of <hi>Lappland,</hi> and <hi>Finnland</hi> as Aſſiſtants: But none of theſe Furies durſt ſhew themſelves, or give the leaſt ſignification of their being there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whilſt our great <hi>Hero</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:59471:53"/> was on the ſhore; knowing that by the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Virtue of his Sword, they muſt all have been diſperſed, their Charmes diſſolved; and their Kingdom deſtroyed; therefore they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him with a great Serenity whilſt on the Land: But now having got him on the Watry Stage, they reſolve to ſhew all their Mallice, to joyne all their Force, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all their Helliſh Arts towards his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
               <p>Scarce were they got three Leagues from the ſhore, before the Little primate was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Shoales of Witchy Syrens, danc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the top of the Water, combing their blew Locks, and Singing their Ominous Notes; which were Intended for the Funeral dirges and Exequies of the great <hi>Patrick,</hi> and his Ships-Company.</p>
               <p>Many of which ſeemed ſtrangely pleaſed at the Novelty of the ſight; till the Sea Riſing, the Waves claſhing, the Billowes Roaring, the Skie Darkened, and Flaſhing with Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeous Fireballs, convinced them, that theſe Watry Nimphs were the unlucky forerunners of moſt deſtructive Tempeſts. Now indeed was the face of things altered to the greateſt diſadvantage; the Air was ſo pitchy-black with the horrid vizour drawn over the Horizon that they could ſcarce diſcerne one the other, unleſs ſometime by the Flaſhes of Lightening; which
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59471:53"/> made the ſturdy Axel-tree to crack again with its loud roaring Thunder, The trembling Veſſel was kickt about on the Surges like a Foot-ball in <hi>Tuttle-Fields;</hi> ſometimes moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Clouds, by and by ſink down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween watry Mountains, that ſeem'd on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide to be tumbling in upon her; the Keell crackt, the main-Maſt was broken, and the Seamen now reduced to deſperation; that they could have been content to drown for fear of farther Danger; Only the undaunted Champion amidſt all this diſorder ſtood with his unconquerable Sword drawn, as if he would Challenge Neptune, and all the Gods of the Ocean; no more was he diſmayed at the rolling of the Sea, then if he had been at Olindors Table; but like a Son of true Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour had his Courage moſt Elevated in the loweſt Ebb of Adverſity, and caſting a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Aſpect on the inſulting Billows; <hi>Proud Waves</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>think not by your loud clamour, and impetuous noiſe to daunt him that values not all the Violence of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; for were I aſtride on one your curled backs, my great Soul ſhould ſo buoy me up, that I would deſpiſe a Squardron of</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, <hi>or a Troop of your Gygantick</hi> Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athans. Still the noiſe of the Tumultuous Air grew Lowder, and was augmented by the ſchrieks and cryes of divers friendly Spirits
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59471:54"/> which ſurrounded the Ship; and caſting his Eye towards the miſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Maſt, our <hi>Patrick</hi> eſpied the Spirit of the great Sorcereſs <hi>Kalyb,</hi> his old Adverſary; ſhe indeed was the main raiſer of all this horrid Tempeſt; for no ſooner had ſhe perceived the diſſolver of her Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Charmes ſet foot on that unlucky Iſland; but ſtraight ſhe whiſpers among all the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> what extraordinary Perſon our Famous <hi>Hero</hi> was; How belov'd by the Gods, and brought into the World under ſuch an Aſpect, as would certainly make him Victorious over all that oppoſe him: He hath already <hi>(conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſhe)</hi> ruined me, and deſtroyed my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Empire: But let us try what our united Forces can do towards his Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, that our Infernal Kingdom may no more be over-maſtred by his proud Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſaid, they all conſented to endeavour the drowning of our Mighty Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion on the Ocean: But no ſooner had he eſpied the ſhade of the Helliſh <hi>Kalyb;</hi> but fixing his piercing Eye upon her Airy form: <hi>Baſe Hagg</hi> (quoth he) <hi>and haſt thou yet ſuch intereſt in the lower World, that thou canſt ſuborn and raiſe ſuch Violence againſt Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane race; Know, that I</hi> Patrick <hi>have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined thy final overthrow, and by the power of this Sword (whoſe force thou haſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59471:54"/> already felt) I conjure thee not to ſtir from that place, until my vertuous Hand ſend thy Fantaſtick form into the Empty Aire.</hi> Thus ſaid he, ordered his Men to hoiſt him up to the Maſt, where being drawn up by the Tackling, and Elevated juſt of a heigth even with the Spectre of the Witch, he let drive a blow with his Inchanted Sword, that you might have ſeen the Spirit ſplit in two parts, which immediatly vaniſhed into the Air, and diſſolved it ſelf in a Pillar of Smoaky At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms: All the other <hi>Demons</hi> with hideous yells and infernal noiſes, leaving the Veſſel to purſue her Voyage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Adventures in the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Countries.</head>
               <p>NO ſooner were theſe Goblins diſperſed, but the Sky was ſo clear, you could not diſcern the ſign of a Cloud; the Ocean was as ſmooth as a Billiard Table, and all things appeared as if there had been no Storm at all; the very Maſts and Shrouds which ſeemed to have been broken, were on ſearch found ſound, and without defect: Only the Seamen paſſing through ſo many Scenes of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59471:55"/> Miracles were almoſt Petrifyed with wonder. Now might you ſee the proud Frigat ſliding o're the ſmiling Main, before the eaſie blaſt of a gentle gale, viewing her ſtately Maſts, and glittering Sterne in the Chriſtal Flood, whilſt Silver-Whitings, Enammell'd Salmons, and broad Turbants, of their owne accord preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves on the deck to feaſt the Princely Champion, to whom <hi>Neptune</hi> ſeemed to have reſigned the Dominion of the Sea. Nor was the Lord of the Airy Region behind hand with his preſents to our Valiant <hi>Hero,</hi> for Duck, Teal, and Widgeon, with all other ſorts of Water Fowle came to the Ship in ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, that they were forced to caſt many of them over into the Sea.</p>
               <p>Now entering the <hi>Mediteranian</hi> Sea, they paſſed by the Rich Countryes of <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and the Coaſt of <hi>Barbary;</hi> and putting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of the Ports belonging to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples,</hi> they furniſhed their Ship with ſuch Neceſſaries as they ſtood in need of; and then continued their Voyage towards the <hi>Archipellago:</hi> where meeting with two great Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lies belonging to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Port, they were ſaluted with a Thundring Broad-Side from the firſt, which laid the Main-Maſt flat upon Deck; ſo that it was in vain to hope by flight to Eſcape their fury: But had the Veſſel had all her Whings, the great <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:59471:55"/> who never knew what 'twas to turn his back upon danger; bravely animated his men to a Noble defence, aſſuring them, if once the <hi>Turks</hi> came to Grapple with him, they ſhould dearly pay for. the damage they had ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by them; then the other Gally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, Gaulled the other ſide of our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions Ship with ſhowres of ſmall ſhot; but they found not the brave <hi>Iriſh</hi> Knight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull to any of their Attacques; for he ſo well played his Port-holes, that he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive divers breaches his ſhot had made in the huge ſides of their large Gallies; beſides, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their men that had been laid upon Deck by his Muſquets: The brave reſiſtance that our Noble Chevalier made, ſtriking no ſmall Terrour into the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Commanders; who being much incenſed to ſee two great Gallies ſo defeated by a ſmall Friggot; one of them with furious reſolution clapping on his grapling Irons, endeavoured to board the ſhip of our Noble <hi>Patrick,</hi> but was preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Courage: for no ſooner perceived he that the veſſels were linked together, but forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with with a Courage Exceeding all but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he leapt on Board the <hi>Turk,</hi> and in little time had covered the Deck, with Bodies that were mowed down like ſtubble by his Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sword; then ſeeing the way clear to the Captain, he made up to him with ſuch brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59471:56"/> that the Infidel, was going to deliver him his Cimeter; <hi>Know baſe Dogg</hi> (ſaid the mighty <hi>Patrick) That thy Fawning ſhall not ſo Reconcile me to thy Beſtial Submiſſion, but I will ſend thy black Soul, to tell thoſe that are ſent before thee, that thy Brutiſh Cruelties, have received their juſt Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence at my Unconquerable Hand.</hi> And at that word giving him a downright blow upon the Head, he broke his Cimeter, with which he endeavoured to defend himſelf, and parted his Head in two parts juſt in the midſt; ſo that one half falling on the right ſhoulder, and the other on the left; and in this Poſture carried them into the other World, as a double Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy to the Valour of <hi>St. Patrick.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining few in that Gally ſeeing the Fate of their Leader, and fellow Souldiers, fell at his feet, beſeeching him to ſpare their Contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lives, that they might make known among their Country men, the High Praiſes due to his Inimitable Valour. His generous Heat being pacified with their humble Submiſſions, eaſily was prevailed upon to give them their worthleſs Lives: Then ſecuring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one of their own Hatches; he turned to ſee what was become of the other Gally; but her Commander ſeeing the Fate of his Brother Pyrate, had wiſely Conveyed his Veſſel ſo far out of the Storm, that it being near Night,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59471:56"/> and <hi>St. Patricks</hi> Veſſel much diſabled, he thought not fit at that time to make after Her: but ordering his men to take notice of what loſs had hapned amongſt the Turks, they found that two Hundred and Eighty had fallen by the alone hand of <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> beſides the Captain: which Bodies having been thrown over Board, they returned to Examine the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of their Prize, which could not well be Computed, ſhe being moſt Richly Loaden with abundance of Silks; beſides great ſtore of Gold, Pearl, and Spices. The greateſt part whereof, he like a Generous Captain diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted amongſt his Souldiers, the better to Incourage them in another Difficulty; and counting his own Loſs, he found but one of his men Killed, and three Wounded; ſo that reckoning the many Slain and Wounded in that other Gally that went off, this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be as ſtrange a Victory as perhaps any Story makes mention of.</p>
               <p>The greateſt part of that Night was ſpent in unloading the Gally, by taking out the Choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Goods, and Stowing them in their own Frigat; ſo that by the next morning they had little to do but to fit their Veſſel the beſt they could for the remainder of their Voyage; which began now to ſhorten. They had a reſerve on Board for ſuch Accidents, and in little time had fitted on new Shrouds, mended their Sails,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59471:57"/> and repaired the Maſt: So leaving the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the conduct of the few Slaves that remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in her, They made with all the Sail they could to the Country of Greece, and in few weeks came in ſight of the Iſle of <hi>Chios;</hi> and makeing to the Harbour, they ſpent ſome dayes there; in diſpoſeing of ſuch Commodities as they thought good to part with; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them with ſuch Neceſſaries as they ſtood in need of. Here likewiſe they met with ſome Engliſh Merchant, by whom they ſent home word of their ſafe Arrival on that Coaſt, and of the ſtrange Adventures performed by the famous <hi>St. Patrick</hi> by the way. Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from <hi>Chios,</hi> the Heroick Champion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his Reſolution for the Continent of <hi>Grecia;</hi> intending by Land to Travel to the Mighty City build by the Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> of the which place, that Age talked Wonders; ſo in few days Arriving at—a Port of <hi>Dalmatia;</hi> he took a Lodging for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Page <hi>Mac,</hi> providing a convenient ſtable for <hi>Crapiero,</hi> of whom you have heard nothing a long time, the wooden Horſe having been in his ſtead: but now we have brought our Knight on ſhore, we ſhall have occaſion to mention him in our Travels. <hi>St. Patrick</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Landed ſuch principal things as he moſt eſteemed; freely gave the Veſſel, with the reſt of the <hi>Cargo,</hi> to the Seamen; who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59471:57"/> they met with ſo great a Booty at leaving their great Maſter; (whoſe bounty was as his Valour, above the reſt of Mankind) yet could they not part with him without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Tears; proteſting that their Captains pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was more valued by them than the Riches of the <hi>Indies,</hi> nay, dearer than their own Lives: So great impreſſion had his high Courage made, even in men of ſo low a make; notwithſtanding, in Obedience to his Command, here they parted.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>St. Patrick rescueing a young woman who was being assaulted by a Satyr</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. How St. <hi>Patrick</hi> fought with the huge <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian Bembo,</hi> and overcame him.</head>
               <p>OVR Champion had not reſted long at the Grand <hi>Seigniors</hi> Court, when (the Fame of his former Atchievments being ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the World) A Monſtrous Tartar ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived alſo at <hi>Conſtantionople,</hi> where he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried certain dayes, bidding defiance to all the Knights about the Court, but none durſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to accept of his Challenge; wherefore hearing of a Stranger lately arrived, who was Famous for Chivalry, he ſends his Lacquey early in the Morning to St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Lodging with a Challenge; who when he knocked at the door, <hi>Mack</hi> lets him in, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59471:59"/> asks his buſineſs; he anſwered, that his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was with his Maſter, that he had a Letter for him, from the Great and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Bembo,</hi> which required a preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Well ſayes <hi>Mack,</hi> if you pleaſe to let me have the letter, and you ſhall have the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer anon; which he did. <hi>Mack</hi> carryes the Letter to his Maſter being in bed, who when he had opened it, he found the Extent of it to Thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Renowned Knight,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HEaring of the great Fame, which by thy Gallantry thou haſt acquired in all places where thou haſt been in this part of the World; I deſire to be further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as to the Truth of it; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing ſo Satisfying in this Point, as Experience; I have ſent you this Challenge, that to Morrow Morning you may meet me well Armed in the Liſt, before the <hi>Serag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio;</hi> where your Valour ſhall be fully tryed by</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Bembo.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Patrick</hi> no ſooner had read the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, but he called for Pen, and Ink, and returned this Anſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:59471:60"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Knight,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>FOR ſo I muſt call you, being altogether a Stranger to you; ſince you are pleaſed to paſs ſo many worthy Knights in <hi>Greece,</hi> and to expreſs your deſire of putting your Valour to tryal with me, to Morrow in the Liſt before the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> I heartily accept, both of the Time and Place, with this proviſo, that the Grand <hi>Segniors</hi> leave be obtained to it; which I my ſelf ſhall endeavour to procure: Whereas you ſay that my Valour ſhall be fully tryed, it muſt be Deeds, and not Words that ſhall do it; however expect to be there looked for by</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Patrick.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Our Champion no ſooner diſpatched the Meſſenger, but preſently he makes his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Grand <hi>Segnior</hi> (whom he found walking in his Garden with a great train of Courtiers) in theſe words; Moſt Renowned Monarch, <hi>The Report that Fame hath made of thy Greatneſs, and the magnificence of thy Court over all the World, hath invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me hither, and now I lye under a Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from a Stranger, who was ſo bold
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59471:60"/> as to appoint the Liſts before your Majeſties</hi> Seraglio, <hi>the place of our Rancounter (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as asking your Majeſties leave); but for my part, I have been more Civilly Educated; therefore (am I come now to proſtrate my ſelf at your Imperial Feet, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that for the Love you have to Chivalry, and your Royal Favors ſhewed to Strangers, and particularly to my ſelf, we may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to morrow morning to try our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the foreſaid Liſts.</hi> The Emperor ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him what the Knight was that thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf able to Enter the Liſts: Why may it pleaſe your Majeſty, ſaith he, I know no more of him as yet, but only that he ſubſcribeth himſelf <hi>Bembo,</hi> which I ſuppoſe is his Name; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the grand Segnior ſeemed extreamly concerned, telling him, that he greatly feared the Event: For ſaith he, the <hi>Bembo</hi> is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Gyant than an ordinary man, and has been a long time in <hi>Greece,</hi> and Challenged many, but none of all our Knights durſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him, except two; And what then, he plaid as a Cat would do with a Mouſe, ſo great was the diſparity in the ſtrength: I am not in any reſpect affraid of him, anſwered he: If he ſhould borrow the ſtrength of a Rock, and the Courage of a Lyon, ile venture all, ſo that I may have your Majeſties Conſent as to the place appointed. With all my heart (anſwered
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59471:61"/> the Emperour) and taking the Champion by the hand, I know ſaith he, thou art one whoſe Sword hath brought thy Fame from the ends of the Earth, and now when the Perecious Iewel (your Honour) ſhould in the leaſt be ſtained in our Court, I would chooſe to forgo infinite Treaſures; yet I am not out of hopes, but will make the Knight feel the weight of thine. I doubt it not in the leaſt (replyed the other) for I think every hour a day till I ſee him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St. Patrick</hi> having obtained the Emperours Licence, with ſo great Expreſſions of Kindneſs beſides; he preſently Retired to his Lodging, gave orders to <hi>Mac</hi> to have a ſpecial care that <hi>Capriero</hi> ſhould be well fed that night, for that he was to be put to Task next morning: Truſty <hi>Mac</hi> neglected nothing that could be for his Maſters Intereſt and Advantage, rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up <hi>Capriero</hi> with ſuch things as he had provided for him, ſo that by his Prauncing and Bouncing, he had almoſt broke down the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, none being able to Command him, but his Maſter alone.</p>
               <p>No ſooner began the Chirping Birds to Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the approaching ſhining of bright <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora,</hi> but our Champion began to make ready for the work of the day; and about eight a Clock, he preſented himſelf in the Liſts, clad in his Rich Glittering Armour upon his ſtately
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59471:61"/> Prauncing Steed, expecting the Emperors coming, who about an hour after appeared from his Royal Pallace, with a Magnificent Train of Knights and Ladyes in great Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: the Emperor having ſate upon a Throne erected for the purpoſe, and all the Princes and Ladyes being placed according to their Rank; They began with wonder to view the Stately Champion who was upon Horſe-back within the Liſts; greatly admiring his State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Body, his Amiable Features, and Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Meen, wiſhing heartily that he might be Victor. As they were thus taken up with him, behold the fierce Tartar entred the Liſt, with Innumerable Tokens of Incomparable Valour, which made many ſear how it would go with the Comely Knight, (for ſo they called St. <hi>Patrick.</hi>) But the Pagan com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up cloſe to him, ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now Knight, ſeeing the time for trying thy Valour with Deeds, is come, there is no reaſon to delay it, but in the nameing of the Judge; ſince one of us muſt of neceſſity remain for ever Breathleſs in the Field, therefore I would know whom you would nominate for Judge. That queſtion is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in many reſpects</hi> (replyed the other) <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I appoint the Emperor himſelf, who ſits there for Judge. I had not thought thy Pride ſo great</hi> (ſaid the Pagan) <hi>but
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59471:62"/> ſince it is ſo, I am content that the Emperor be judg to them I intend to preſent thy Head before I leave the Liſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The furious Champion thought it no time to trifle any longer with the Barbarous Savage, therefore they turned their Horſes, ſwifter than two light Gallies carried with the force of their full wind blown Sailes, met in the end of their Courſes, breaking their Launces to Shivers without moving in their Saddles. So drawing their glittering Swords, they ran like Lyons one upon another, laying on ſuch blowes as that every one that lookt on, thought they were the laſt. Great abundance of Blood iſſued from both their Armour, but moſt from the Pagans; for though the ſtrength of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour defended his Body in ſome parts of it from Wounding, yet the Combat had not laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an hour, when he found himſelf ſo bruiſed and tyred, that he could hardly keep his Saddle, which made him in a raging Fury Aſſault <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> thruſting at him with a Point with ſuch Force, that he laid him along upon his Saddle; this he ſeconded with a terrible blow upon his Breaſt, before he could reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf, which made him almoſt quite ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. With more ravening Fury turn'd n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the raging Tygre upon his Foe, than no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did our Champion; for caſting his own Shield <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:59471:62"/> his back, he diſcharged ſuch a blow on his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, that he clave it quite aſſunder; then with renewed Force, did they cloſe one with another, with ſuch Rage, that both Horſes and Riders tumbled to the ground; yet had they ſcarcely touched the ground when both were on their feet again. The Pagan having recovered ſome Breath, with freſh ſtrength he aſſaulted his Adverſary, thruſting at him with ſuch Force, that made him yeeld a little ground; yet not ſo much but that he could reach him with ſuch a blow upon the Thigh, as made him tremble: Abundance of blood ſtreaming from it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Pagan abandoning all Fear, Recloſed with him, and with one ſtroak, cut away his Male-ſleeve, drawing much blood after it: This greivous blow he thought to have ſeconded with ſuch another as would end the Controverſy with our Champions Life, but he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much miſtaken; for the other being ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that his Armour was much weakned, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make ſtrength and courage his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor; therefore with his Sword he gave the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſuch a blow upon the Shoulder, that he made the blood guſh out in great meaſure. The fight is now as it were begun afreſh, ſuch Strength and Valor appeared on both ſides, that the beholders were ſo poſſeſt with admiration, that they almoſt thought it a Dream; for the Combat continued four hours
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59471:63"/> without any reſt; therefore with mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they parted a little to breath: St. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> having ſate down in a Chair that was ſet for him of the purpoſe, he began to recount with himſelf, with how little ſucceſs he had fought all that while, his Enemy having as yet as good a proſpect of the Victory as himſelf; therefore he preſently ſtarts up upon his Feet, aſſaulting his Enemy, who was ready for him, with ſuch terrible fury, that both almoſt came to the Ground together; then they claſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one another about the middle, and began to wreſtle like two Gyants; but their ſtrength was ſo equal, that none of them could get his Adverſary thrown down, which made them again betake them to their Swords; then the Spectators obſerving St. <hi>Patrick</hi> to have the better, began to ſhout for Ioy. But the Impatient <hi>Pagan</hi> Curſing and Blaſpheming againſt his Gods, as thinking that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace proceeded from them, run upon his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and with both hands let ſly at him ſuch a blow, that lighting on the ſide of his Helme, he cut away all the Bucklers on the right ſide.</p>
               <p>Now our Champion finding that all the parts of his Armor were thus rendred uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to him, thought it was no time to linger; therefore with his Sword in both hands, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted his Enemy; who in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59471:63"/> received him, and with more horror then the furious Waves bent upon the Flinty Rock, they diſcharged their blows upon their Helmets, ſo that they both fell ſenſleſs to the ground, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> without his Helm, but the other with his Head, Skull and Brains broken, and ſcattered within his Helm. Some would have gone to them, but were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Guard, till it were ſeen, what the effects of their Trance muſt be; but ſtraight was the Victory proclaimed, for the Valiant St. <hi>Patrick</hi> recovering himſelf looked for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; but finding to lye, went to him and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacing his Helm, ſaw that he was quite dead: Then addreſſing himſelf to the Emperour, and to the reſt of the Iudges, demanded whether he had performed the Action to his Honour. One in the Emperors name, replyed thus, <hi>Valiant Knight, The great</hi> Souldan, <hi>with all the reſt of the Judges and Spectators, commanded me to tell you, That your At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievments this day, have been ſuch, as ſhall be enough to perpetuate your memory in this place for ever.</hi> Nay, this was not all, for the Emperour himſelf, with all his Train came to the place to receive the Viccorious Knight; to him he ſpake thus: <hi>Valiant Knight, The force of your Armes hath this day purged our Court from the Aſperſions, which otherwiſe it ſhould undoubtedly lye under,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59471:64"/> by the daily Bravadoes of that inſolent Knight; ask what thou pleaſeſt in compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of thy Valour, and it ſhall forthwith be granted.</hi> To whom our Campion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Renowned Monarch, I reckon my ſelf highly honoured, in that your Greatneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcends to look upon this Service as done for the honour of Thy Court, to which I heartily dedicate it; wiſhing for no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but that I may continue in thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Favour.</hi> Whereupon the Emperour giving him his hand to kiſs, raiſed him from the ground, and demanded who he was; to them, he anſwered, that he was born in the Weſtern parts of the World, but for ſome time Travelled in <hi>Greece;</hi> and that hearing of the ſplendor of the Emperial Court at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he would needs Satisfy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſee it; neither did he then repent his coming thither, for every thing did exactly anſwer his expectations. The Emperour would not ſuffer him to go back to his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but would deeds have him go along with himſelf to Court, where his wounds might be healed by his own Phyſitians, which was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Carefully and Dexterouſly performed, ſo that in few dayes he was perfectly recovered: <hi>Capriero</hi> alſo having been hurt in two places, was intruſted to the care of the Emperors
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59471:64"/> Grooms, who ſo performed their part, that he was well before his Maſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. How <hi>Alphebo, Bemboes</hi> Brother being to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his Brothers Death, was vanquiſhed by St. <hi>Patrick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OVr Champion had not reſted himſelf long after the Conflict with <hi>Bembo,</hi> when newes being gone to <hi>Tartary,</hi> that their Champion was killed at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> his Brother whoſe Name was <hi>Alphebo,</hi> being for Valour and Courage every way equal to <hi>Bembo</hi> himſelf, haſtens with all ſpeed to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> reſolving either to revenge his Brothers death, or elſe never to ſee his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try again. Being arrived, the firſt thing he did, was to enquire for his Name, whoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune it was to overcome the Mighty <hi>Bembo;</hi> which he no ſooner learnt, but he preſently ſends him a moſt provoking Challenge in theſe Termes.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:59471:65"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Preſumptuous Knight,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WHoſe misfortune it was to kill the braveſt Champion in the World; I his only Brother knowing aſſuredly, that thou could'ſt never have done ſuch an Act, but through Treachery, am here arrived to demand ſatisfaction, which I am reſolved to have upon any terms; and that in the very place where thou moſt cowardly murder'd my Valiant Brother; I am reſolved to offer up thy carcaſs, as a Sacrifice to my Gods, and and to carry thy Head in tryumph to my Country, to make ſatisfaction for thy wrong. If thou do not preſently anſwer my Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge (as it is probable thou dareſt not) think not that the Emperours Pallace ſhall protect you, for my reſolution is to have thy life, if I ſhould break through Walls of Braſs for it; therefore your anſwer in haſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Alphebo.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Challenge came to our Champion, as he was walking with the Emperor in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; which he no ſooner rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ived and read, but he let the Emperour ſee it: he having read it over, and obſerving the Mans raſh
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59471:65"/> and inconſiderate way of Writing; turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to St. <hi>Patrick, I perceive</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that theſe two Knights are much of a temper, and I doubt the ſucceſs ſhall prove the ſame to this, as it did to the laſt: I need not adviſe thee what to do, I leave it to thy ſelf; and I queſtion not, but thy Sword is ſharp enough to vindicate thine Honour: What ever time and place thou ſhalt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix, care ſhall be taken that all things may be put in due order; and ſo adue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperour being gone to the Pallace, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> asked the Bearer of the Letter to tarry there a little, and he ſhould have his anſwer preſently, and ſo retired to a Summer Houſe, there writ his anſwer thus,</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir Knight,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IT might be expected from a Man of Armes that he would not undervalue himſelf to invade the Province, not of a ſilly Woman, as you by your <hi>Scolding</hi> Language in your Letter; proves you ſelf to have done. I think it below my ſelf to take particular notice of any paſſage in it, ſo much as to mention it; only know, that your Brother, who hath gone before you, talked almoſt as broadly as you do; but the event proved, that his Tongue had the advantage of his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59471:66"/> hands: And for your part, ſince you have not by his fate received inſtruction; make your ſelf ready, and appear in the ſame place, to morrow morning at eight a Clock; where if you want to know how your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Brother dyed, you ſhall upon your own charges be acquainted with it, by</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Patrick.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Our Champion having diſpatched the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, he went to the Pallace, where he found the Emperour, giving the neceſſary orders for the next day; who deſired that St. <hi>Patrick</hi> would be ſo free with him as to acquaint him of any thing that he might want that were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Action: He replyed, that he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing at preſent, only his Armour was much cut in the laſt Ingagement; whereupon the Emperour went preſently to his Armory, and brought in his own hand, a ſtand of moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Armour, with which he preſented St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> deſiring him to try how it would fit him; which preſently he did, and found it lay as well to his Body, as if it had been made for him; after that the Emperour had diſcourſed a while with him upon the next dayes adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he retired to his Chamber; where cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for <hi>Mac,</hi> he gave him ſtrict orders, that he ſhould look well to <hi>Crapriero,</hi> and ſhould
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59471:66"/> have his Saddle, and other things in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before he went to reſt, which <hi>Mac</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly did. Thus our Champion paſſed over this weariſom night, long looking for the morning, which no ſooner began to appear, but he preſently aroſe from his Bed, and began to put every thing in its own place; having with all ſpeed buckled on his Armour, when he found the appointed time approach, he came from his Chamber, where in the great Hall the Emperour met him, and complemented him at a high rate; and accompanying him to the Gate, he heartily wiſhed him good ſucceſs; and ſo left him to call the Princes and Ladyes of the Court together, that they might follow.</p>
               <p>Our Champion entred the Liſts by the way from the Pallace; where he no ſooner appeared, but all the beholders began to wonder, who it ſhould be, his Change of Armour making them no wiſe ſuſpect, that he was the Champion that had made himſelf ſo famous in that place not long before. The Armour which he wore that day, was of a bright yellow colour, full of half Moons, overcaſt with a ruſſet Coat. The Emperour and the Court had ſcarce ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their Seats when at the other end of the Liſts entred the Tartarian, mounted upon a ſtrong and mighty Courſer: his Warlike Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit was of a ſad Red Colour, with green Bars and golden Gravings; at his Saddle Pummel
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59471:67"/> hung a mighty Mace of Steel; with all which he appeared mighty Terrible to all, except him with whom he had to do.</p>
               <p>Without any other Ceremony, theſe two Warlike Champions, like two Flaſhes of Lightning, ran at one another; at the firſt Rancounter they peirced their Sheilds, the Breaſt-Plate of each ſtaying his Adverſaries Fury, from whence the ſhivers of the broken Launces mounted into the middle Region of the Air; then with the raging Wrath which poſſeſſed both of them alike, they returned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each other, and with the ſtrength of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Arms diſcharging ſuch furious Blowes one upon the other, that all the Beholders expected the Conflict would not laſt long; but they were much miſtaken; the furious Pagan laid on ſo fiercely with his Mace, that <hi>St. Patrick</hi> loſt his Creſt, and had his Head ſore bruiſed; but feeling the ſmart of the blows, and ſeeing his own blood, he with redoubled ſtrength let ſuch ſly at the <hi>Pagan,</hi> that he had almoſt tumbled him from his Saddle; yet it ſo fell out, that he only fell forward upon his Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes neck, ſhedding a great deal of blood through his noſe and eyes.</p>
               <p>Thus they continued for the ſpace of five hours in ſuch a bloody conflict as perhaps the World did never ſee the like: At laſt both of them begining to be weary, and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59471:67"/> that his adverſary ſhould ſtand ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, with the utmoſt of their force, they diſcharged their fury in ſuch ſort, that they ſtruck each other from their Horſes, to the aſtoniſhment of all the beholders. The <hi>Pagan</hi> looſed his Mace in the fall, which was a great loſs to him, they ſcarcely touched the ground, when quicker than could be Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd they were both upon their Feet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but before the <hi>Pagan</hi> could well recover his feet, our Champion gave ſuch a ſtroak with his Sword upon the top of his Shield, that he cut away a piece of it, with all the top of his Helm; an that ſide, this terrible blow made him ſtagger, and look as if he were ready to ſink down upon the place; <hi>St. Patrick</hi> finding now that his Adverſary was in ſuch a maze, he ſeconded this blow with another upon his Thigh, cutting it to the bone. This awakned the <hi>Pagan,</hi> as it were out of a Dream, and ſeeing his own blood colouring the Graſs all-about him, it put him into ſuch a Lyon-like fury, that like a devouring Bear he ran upon his Enemy, who in the ſame manner received him. Thus, as it were, the Battle is began afreſh, with force and fury upon both ſides; the noiſe of their Swords, was heard all over the Emperours Palaces, though Two hundred and fifty Paces diſtant from it. The <hi>Pagan</hi> finding that his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59471:68"/> could handle his Sword with more dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity than himſelf could do; and being now abundantly ſenſible of the want of his truſty Mace, reſolved upon the firſt opportunity to get within him; which the other perceiving, he asked him if he thought it might be any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to him to try his ſtrength in Wreſtling; if it were, he told him that he was content to throw away his Sword, and to try him in any manner, or upon any terms he pleaſed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they both agreed; but withal, they were firſt to take a little breath.</p>
               <p>Having both of them ſat down at a little diſtance one from the other, they began each of them to be more ſenſible of his Wounds; the <hi>Pagan</hi> had received nine very deep wounds, one of which was upon his thigh, which did extremely trouble him, for it bled all the while he ſat: <hi>St. Patrick</hi> hath four all about the Buckling of his Armour, two of which were very deep; his body alſo was very ill bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Pagans</hi> Mace, which did him much hurt.</p>
               <p>However, bethinking with himſelf that for all that was done, the victory was yet uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, he ſtarts up upon his Feet with as much nimbleneſs, as if he had not fought a ſtroak that day: He addreſſeth himſelf to the <hi>Pagan</hi> thus, <hi>Sir Knight</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>We have kept the Emperour and his, all this day
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59471:68"/> looking to no purpoſe, ſo little is done by us on either ſide; that they have no reaſon to be ſatisfied; come therefore, ſince thou haſt thrown away thy Sword, and made it thy choice to determine the quarrel by your Strength, let us trifle away our time no longer.</hi> The <hi>Pagan</hi> ſeemed very ready, and with great Courage advanced towards him; and caſt his mighty Arms about him: Here began a terrible Conflict, the <hi>Pagan</hi> raiſed our Champion from the Ground, and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thrown him upon his Back. He with all his Power held him faſt, and in the mean time, with a Trip, got hold of him faſt by the mindle, by which he was in equal termes with him: Thus they toſſed one another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like two Lyons, for a long ſpace, till at laſt, <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> in a Rage, ſwinging the <hi>Pagan</hi> about, threw him well nigh ſix paces from him; with the force of which, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf fell to the ground; but both were up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with ſuch Nimbleneſs, that all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders were Aſtoniſhed; then with renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed force they clapſed each other about the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which was the beginning of the laſt Scene of this Tragedy, and was as Couragiouſly managed as any of the former; both of them knowing that it could not hold out much longer. The <hi>Pagan</hi> taking his advantage, attempted to throw his Adverſary backward: But the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59471:69"/> other, being as nimble as he was ſtrong, not only kept his feet, but alſo with Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Force lifted up the <hi>Pagan</hi> from the ground, and threw him down again with ſuch a noiſe, as made the ground ſhake; yet after much ſtriving, he got up again. Now the light of <hi>Phaebus</hi> being by this time drencht within the caverns of the Weſtern Ocean, and night ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving covered them with her dark vail; the two Champions cryed out for lights: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Emperor cauſed above a thouſand bright Torches to be lighted; but the Warriers were both of them ſo overcome with this long and tedious Conflict, that if Honour had not been ſo much concerned, which made both of them act above their ſtrength, they could not have ſubſiſted ſo long, eſpecially the <hi>Pagan,</hi> who was wearyed with the Combat, and ſo weakned with the loſs of his Blood, that for every ſtep he made, with his Blood he left it printed on the Graſs: However, finding that by his Sword he was not like to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Adverſary, and being ſtill reſolved either to conquer him, or dye in the place, he to his fatal loſs, joyned with him again, and obſerving a Dagger by <hi>St. Patricks</hi> ſide, he ſnatched it from him, and thought to have run him through the left ſhoulder with it, but the Valiant <hi>St. Patrick</hi> diſdaining thus to be wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his own Weapon, takes hold of the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59471:69"/> 
                  <hi>Pagan</hi> by the wriſt, forcing the Dagger out of his hand, and gives him ſuch a ſtab with it, in the Breaſt, that he fell upon his back. Whereupon our Champion preſently gets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, and with the Dagger in his hand, beſpoke him thus: <hi>Now Knight, know aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, that your Life is in my hand; you may remember your Challenge, and that the contents of it were, that in the ſame place, where I killed your Brother, you ſhould in the ſame manner kill me; yet now you may ſee your folly, in venting your ſelf at ſuch a rate againſt a man whoſe ſtrength you knew not; till your own ſad experience gave you a Proof of it: But for my part, I have learned moderately to manage my Conqueſt; therefore, here I put it in thy Choice, either to dye, or live; if thou'lt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of thy Life, as a complement from my hand, thou ſhalt have it, provided only, that thou acknowledg thy ſelf Overcome.</hi> At this motion, the <hi>Pagan</hi> began to Curſe, and Blaſpheme; Curſing his Gods that had thus left him in his Extremity. <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> asked him the ſecond time, if he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of his Terms, which he disdainfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed: Whereupon, with the Dagger which was ready in his hand, he cut off his head, and held it out to the people. No ſooner they eſpyed it, but they gave ſuch a ſhout, as made
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59471:70"/> all the Rocks reſound: The Emperor imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave orders to his Phyſitians to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany our Champion to the Palace: thither he was carryed in great Triumph, with ſound of Trumpet, and other Warlike Inſtruments; perſons of all Ranks and Qualities, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their kindneſs to him by all poſſible tokens of Love and Affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. St. <hi>Patrick</hi> ſets out from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his one Country; he comes to the King of <hi>Sicilies</hi> Court, and of his Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant behaviour there.</head>
               <p>OVR renowned Champion, having pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed immortal Trophies of Fame all the World over; conſidering with himſelf, how long he had been abſent from his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, and from enjoying the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Society, and Fellowſhip of his deareſt Friends and Relations, (who by length of time, as alſo conſidering the great hazards to which he was daily expoſed; began to deſpair, of ever ſeeing him again, reſolves now to return home, and paſs the reſt of his dayes more obſcurely. Therefore when he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured of the wounds which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59471:70"/> in the laſt Rancounter with the Tartar He reſolved to take hold of the firſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for communicating his purpoſe to the Emperor: Occaſion ſoon after offers it ſelf; for the Emperor being at his mornings walk in his Arbour, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> addreſſeth himſelf to him thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illuſtrious Monarch, I make bold to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt your Majeſty from your greater thoughts, by preſenting my mean requeſt to you: Sir, I am a Man, a great part of whoſe dayes have been ſpent in deeds of Armes, and now I am reſolved by your Imperial leave, to return home to my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, there to give my ſelf to the Contemplation of Supernatural things; This therefore is my requeſt, that it may pleaſe your Majeſty to give me leave to depart your Court with thoſe Marks of Honour, that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually are conferred upon ſuch as have brought themſelves under no Stigma of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach under your ſervice; higher I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not, and lower I preſume, your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will not place me.</hi> The Emperor not dreaming that St. <hi>Patrick</hi> would ever leave his Court, was hugely ſurpriſed, when he heard him thus talk of his ſpeedy reſolution; and after having for half an hour ſtood amazed as if he knew not what to ſay, at length he breaks out in a paſſionate manner. <hi>What,</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:59471:71"/> ſaith he, <hi>You whom of all the Knights in the world I moſt eſteem, and by whom of all the Knights that ever appeared at my Court, I thought my ſelf moſt Honoured, Wilt thou now after your having purchaſed ſuch a vaſt Stock of Fame; nay which is more, gain'd my Affections in ſuch a meaſure? Wilt thou I ſay, after all this, leave us thus obſcurely? I hope you will not, therefore I deſire you may conſider better before you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve. If you want any thing that can give you ſatisfaction which my Dominions can afford, let me know it, and doubt not but it ſhall be granted.</hi> St. <hi>Patrick</hi> replyed, that nothing moved him to leave his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Court, but his longing to ſee his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country; and that if he were to paſs his time as he had formerly done, no Monarch ſhould command him more than he.</p>
               <p>The Emperor finding that no intreaties could prevail with our Champion to tarry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer with him, did at length (though much againſt his heart) Condeſcend to let him go, cauſing alſo rich Preſents to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for him: but St. <hi>Patrick</hi> humbly refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all; telling the Emperor, that thoſe coſtly things were ſitter for Ladies, than for ſuch as he was.</p>
               <p>Thus after a great many Ceremonies and Complements paſt on both ſides, he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59471:71"/> from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with no other reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue but truſty <hi>Mack,</hi> and <hi>Capriero,</hi> directing his courſe towards <hi>Sicily;</hi> being come to the <hi>Mauritaman</hi> Coaſt, he hyred a ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to tranſport him to <hi>Sicily,</hi> which no ſooner was under Sail, but the Winde and the Element began a ſtrife, as it were which of them ſhould be moſt ſerviceable to him; ſo that in a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time than one can imagine, he came to a Harbour in a remote part of the Country. Having landed, and walked a while by the Sea ſide, there came to him an Old Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Lady all diſordered with grief, having her Vail in her hand, and Hair hanging about her ſhoulders, our Champion upon her approach ſtood ſtill, expecting that ſhe would ſpeak to him, which ſhe her ſelf intended; but when ſhe went about it, ſuch floods of tears roſe in her Eyes, that ſhe could not utter one word: whereupon he breaks off to her thus: <hi>I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Lady, that you are one whoſe Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are great, ſo much is expreſſed by your looks; but if they be not paſt remedy, be pleaſed to acquaint me with it, and I ſhall indeavour to ſee you ſet to rights.</hi> The Old Gentlewoman, when ſhe heard ſuch words from ſo Gallant-like a Perſon, began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive, and to gather ſome hopes, that he might be the man that ſhould eaſe not only her, but all <hi>Sicilie</hi> of their grief; whereupon ſhe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:59471:72"/> abruptly break her ſilence thus. <hi>Valiant Knight, who knows but that by the Gods, thou art or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to make</hi> Sicilie <hi>happy; and ſent hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at this time for that end; therefore I beſeech you make haſte to the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, or I fear you may come too late.</hi> Our Knight began to be a little aſtoniſhed at the Ladyes relation, and therefore deſired her in ſhort to be more plain in it. <hi>That I will do</hi> (quoth ſhe) <hi>in as plain and ſhort terms as I can. Know then Heroick Champion, that the fair</hi> Honoria, <hi>the King of</hi> Sicilies <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Daughter, is this day (in all probability) to fall into the hands of a Monſter: The manner thus; There liveth in a Forreſt not far from the Kings Pallace, a huge creature ſhap'd like a man; but no doubt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſome monſterous copulation; for though he ſeems to have ſomthing of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a man, yet his terrible bigneſs, and moſt fierce actions makes many doubt what he is. This Gyant or Monſter having upon a day, unfortunately ſeen the Beautiful</hi> Honoria <hi>as ſhe paſſed in her Chariot through the wood, came within a few dayes, and very imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly demanded her of her father: The King viewing his features, and conſidering his deformity, diſdainfully refuſed him; whereupon immediately he departed, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to make her a dear</hi> Honoria <hi>to</hi> Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59471:72"/> 
                  <hi>and accordingly ever ſince he has made it his work to burn and deſtroy the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where ever he comes, not ſparing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Age or Sex; none dares oppoſe, for his ſtrength is ſo terrible that men ſeems but like Rats in his Clutches. The King finding the great loſs the Country ſuſtained by his cruelty, ſent him an Herald, acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that if he did not (againſt this day) find one who ſhould fight him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and overcome him, he ſhould have his daughter. Now the day is come, and none hath as yet appeared at Court that offers battle to the Monſter; therefore, now Knight, think, what you have to do; If you will venture for Honour, do; if not, forbear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This full and perfect account ſo filled our Champion with an itching to be at it, that he could ſcarce contain himſelf; ſo he asked the Lady which way he ſhould ſteer his courſe to find out the place of the Battell; ſhe told him, that if he ſhould ride to the right hand untill he came to a little Brook, that Brook would lead him to the very place, where he ſhould ſee the Giants Tent ready pitched; but that ſhe was afraid there ſhould be none elſe there but himſelf. Without any more, S. <hi>Patrick</hi> ſets his Spurs to his Horſe, commanding <hi>Mack</hi> to obſerve the Ladies direction, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him; and in the ſpace of an hour he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59471:73"/> came within ſight of the Tent, which was of a prodigious bigneſs: he alighted without the field, and tyed <hi>Capriero</hi> to a Buſh; then he began to advance towards the Tent. But as he was tying his horſe to the Buſh, one of the Kings ſervants who had been ſent out as a private ſpye, ſees him at a diſtance; who taking notice of his extraordinary appearance, ran back in all haſt, and told the King of it; whereupon the King immediately Summons the whole Court together, and went out all in their Chariots towards the place.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Patrick</hi> having made no great haſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Tent, the King was within ſight of the Field before the Gyant appeared; for St. <hi>Patrick</hi> as ſoon as he came near the Tent, made a ſign upon the roof of it with his Launce for the Gyant to come out; but the Gyant pretending he was not ready, gave the King time to enter the field before he appeared: alſo people of all ſorts having heard that a ſtrange Champion was arrived, came to ſee the Event. The Gyant at length comes out of his Tent, with eyes full of Terror, having in his hand an Iron Mace of ſuch bigneſs, that no ordinary man could carry a piece of Wood of ſuch a ſize: He no ſooner ſaw his Antagoniſt, but he ſtruck at him with ſuch a Force, that (he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nimbly leapt aſide) it made the whole Field to ſhake: <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> before the Gyant could
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:59471:73"/> recover his Mace, runs his Launce through his ſhoulder Bone; the Monſter ſeeing his own Blood, became as mad as any Devil in Hell; Whereupon lifting up his fearful Inſtrument, let ſuch a Blow at the other, as might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to cleave a Rock; but <hi>St. Patrick</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided it likewiſe; which made the Gyant in a rage, throw away his Mace, and draw his Terrible Sword; which when it appeared out of the Sheath, looked a great deal bigger than the Oar of a Schuller; with it he runs upon his Enemy with all his Force, who received him in the like manner: Thus the Confliſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins a freſh; the Gyant had ſtrength, but not art to manage his Sword. <hi>St. Patrick,</hi> though he was ſhort of the Gyant in Strength, yet his ſingular dexterity in handling the Sword, made him have the Advantage of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in that point, which he did not fail to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove to the Life; for they had not Fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half an hour, when the Gyant had five deep Wounds in his Body; which did very much abate his Strength; and put him in ſuch Fury, that his Sword proving as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable to him, as his Mace did; threw it away alſo, and runs in upon his Antagoniſt, hoping to make his clutches do that which his Weapons could not do: But <hi>St. Patrick</hi> not willing to commit himſelf into his hands, whom he believed to exceed him ſo much in ſtrength,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59471:74"/> holds the point of his Sword to him, to keep him off him; but he ruſhing forward with all his force, not regarding any hazard, run him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf directly upon the Sword, and made it go directly through his Body. When he had thus received his Fatal Wound, he ſcrieched out in ſo terrible a manner, that he made both Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth reſound; tumbling down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground like a Rock. The Spectators they ſhout aloud for joy, eſpecially the King; for the joy he conceived in having his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try freed from ſuch a terrible Enemy, and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noria</hi> for being quit of ſo unpleaſant a Lover. The Victory being abſolutely obtained, the King himſelf came towards St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> where he was reſting his wearied Body, by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſs of the Gyant, and invites him home with him, which the other willingly conſented to.</p>
               <p>Being conveyed by ſome Knights to a moſt ſumptuous Apartment in the Palace, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened himſelf of his Armour, which the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> preſented to him, which by this laſt Engagement, was ſo ſhattered to pieces, that it was now quite uſeleſs for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further ſervice: His Head-Piece was beat together like an old Pewter-Platter, by the Gyants terrible Mace; ſo that if the Head it ſelf, had not been of more than ordinary hardneſs, it had gone ill with him; as for his Body-Armour, though it was one of the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:59471:74"/> Beſt, that the eyes of man ever did behold, the morning before the Conflict; yet, ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably was it cut, that one could ſcarce ſee an inch of it whole from head to foot; which made the Rnights who ſtood by, exceedingly pleaſe themſelves, in paſſing their Iudgment upon it in merriment. Some asking our Champion, What he would ſell his bundle of old Rags for? Another alledged, that he doubted, whether any Knight in <hi>Sicily</hi> (for as well as they were acquainted with Armour) if this bundle were preſented to them, as it lay, could tell what it was. A third ſaid, Our Champion would do well to take e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial notice of every piece, as he laid it by, that he might know how to put it in its own place, when he had uſe for his Armour: for I will aſſure you (ſaith he) Sir Knight, you'le need timely Advertiſement to make ready; for if the Enemy ſhould aſſault us, your Tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is a little out of Order. Well, well, Gentlemen, anſwered he, I ſee you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be merry, and rather than you ſhould want a fit Subject, my diſtreſſed Armour muſt be laid hold on, which I very well allow of; but I muſt tell you, the cutting of it was no matter of Laughter to me, for I muſt confeſs, I was never in my Life ſo hardly Engaged, as I was with this Gyant: I knew his ſtrength did by many Degrees exceed;
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59471:75"/> mine; and beſides, I was much out of order, with my long and tedious Iourney from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> which did not a little impair both my ſtrength and nimbleneſs; and I muſt further confeſs, that if he had had the way of managing his ſtrength with ſuch Knightly Dexterity as was becoming, I did look upon him to have been too hard for any Knight that beareth Armour, under the Sun; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, when I found where his Strength lay, I began to know how to deal with him, and accordingly I managed my buſineſs, ſo as all things happened according to my expectation; Nay, replyed one of the Knights, whether things fell out according to your expectation or not, I know not; but this I muſt ſay, (though I love not to Flatter any one to his face) that I did never in my Life ſee ſo ſeemingly unequal a match, have ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Iſſue: For when you both appeared in the Field together, me thought I could make no ſitter Compariſon betwixt, than of a Man and a Mountain, ſo diſproportioned were Statures one to the other; I lookt upon your Adverſary fitter to overturn Rocks, than to fight with Men; neither do I believe that I was miſtaken of his Strength, for he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make no more of the huge Mace he had in his Paw, than if it were no heavier than a ruſh: yet, ſaith he, (caſting his Eye upon the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59471:75"/> Fineneſs of St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Armour, which lay upon the Table) I think truly the loſs you have ſuſtained in your Armour, might be a ſufficient ground, of a new Challenge, if the Monſter had ſurvived. Come, come, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he, that loſs is no loſs at all, if rightly conſidered; for I am certain his loſs is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that did it; nor do I in the leaſt doubt but he was ſufficiently ſenſible of it before his ſoul and his body parted; for one might read in his very looks, that he repented his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and that if it were to do again, he would adviſe before he ventured. It is true, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another of the Knights, he was a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Fellow to look on; but I doubt, that if we be asked by Strangers, (as undoubtedly we ſhall) concerning his exact dimentions, both as to his length and breadth, whether any of us can ſatisfie them. Indeed anſwered another, I cannot; Nor I, ſaith the third. Come, ſaith the fourth, that is a thing eaſie; for this Valiant Champion has laid him at his full length in yonder Field, (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out at the window to the Field where he lay); ſo that now one may ſafely meaſure him by inches from top to toe: Let any too of us go then, and for our own and others ſatisfaction, bring his exact dimentions: To which they all agreed, and ſo two of them went; but as they were going out at the door,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59471:76"/> one of the reſt calls merrily after them. Gentlemen, ſaith he, I hope you know your buſineſs, and what you are going about. One of the Knights going out at door, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about, and asked him, What made him queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that? why, ſayes he, I would have you forget none of your Neceſſaries for your work; for you know Mathematicians, when they who take the Dimenſions of a Hill or Mountaine, they make uſe of the Quadrant, without which they cannot aſſure themſelves whether they have done their buſineſs as they ought, or not. St. <hi>Patrick</hi> ſmiling at the Ieſt, ſaid: Pray Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen go about your work, for we have ſport enough already, from the fellows Carrion, and my Armour; ſo that you ſee, how one mans raſhneſs may be a Subject of Divertiſement to many: The two Knights went accordingly about their Buſineſs, with a meaſuring Linet; but their Line proving too ſhort upon Tryal, they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſend for more, and themſelves to wait by the Carcaſs, until it was brought them; then they went a ſecond time to Work, and in the firſt place they meaſured his full length, which they found to have been Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yards, three quarters, and Seven inches; then they meaſured the circumference of his Body about the middle; but this they found very difficult, becauſe of the weight of his Trunk; yet by the help of ſome that looked
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59471:76"/> on, they raiſed the Body ſo far from the ground, as to get the Line put under him, and bringing it about, they found his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference to be five yards and an half; laſt of all, they meaſured the Length betwixt his Eyes, which appeared to have been Twenty Inches full: Thus having ſatisfyed their own Curioſity in viewing, and meaſuring of him, they returned to the Palace.</p>
               <p>They were no ſooner gone from the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſs, but Six men in Armour, came from the adjacent Wood, and putting the Body up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Huge Engine, ſomewhat reſembling a Hearſe, drawn by Six Horſes, and as it ſeemed, made of purpoſe for that end; they with a great deal of ſeeming grief, conveyed it to the wood; where, as ſoon as it entered, there begun ſuch a fearful crying and bellowing of men and women together, that St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> who all the while looked out at his Chamber-window, ſaid, Merrily. I wiſh he has not been my Country man, for theſe lamentable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequies, reſembling our Iriſh Women, makes me deeply ſuſpect it.</p>
               <p>The two Knights, being come back again, as they were giving an account of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the King enters the room, who ſeeing two of the Knights ſtanding, one at one end of the room, the other, at the other, having a Line extended betwixt them, each of them
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59471:77"/> holding it by the end; asked them what it meant to them? they replyed: May it pleaſe your Majeſty, this is the exact Length of the Gyant, which fell by the hands of this Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Knight (pointing to St. <hi>Patrick):</hi> The King, though he did ſee the Gyant fall, yet was he Aſtoniſhed when he ſaw his Length, by the Line; nor could he hardly be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe it, untill they ſhewed him his Thickneſs alſo; whence he concluded, that the Prodigious Bulk of his Body, had made him miſtake, as to his Length; but when he ſaw the ſpace betwixt his Eyes, he could by no means be perſwaded to believe it, till with many Aſſeverations the two Knights who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him, averred it: The King hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng heard and ſeen all that paſſed, walked five or ſix times about the room, in a profound ſilence, with his eyes fixed upon the ground: At laſt he breaks out with great Paſſion, and ſaid, (directing his words to St. <hi>Patrick) O Knight, without reproach, thou Mirrour of Chival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, had the Fates Honoured</hi> Sicily <hi>with thy Birth, I would look upon thee, as one of the Preciouſeſt Jewels in my Regal Diadem; but however, it was otherwiſe ordered by the uncontroulable Powers, yet I purpoſe, that if Honour or Preferment, the Riches and Glory of</hi> Sicily, <hi>may be of any weight with you, that henceforth thou ſhalt live
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59471:77"/> with me, and partake of my Fortune: I doubt not, but that you had Offers of this Nature from other Princes, before you came hither, yet, this does no ways diſcourage me from inviting you, nor put me out of hopes, but that you will comply with my deſire; if there were nothing elſe to move you to it, but the examples of the many Valiant Champions, Famous over all the World, who after they had viſited the moſt Famous Courts in the World, yet were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent at laſt, to take up their reſidence with my predeceſſors at this Court. And for you Knight, if you will ſtay, here I paſs my Royal Promiſe before theſe Gentlemen, that you ſhall have as much Honour and Reſpect, as any Knight that ever was in</hi> Sicily.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Patrick</hi> was mightily ſurpriſed at this, fearing that if he ſhould perſiſt in his former reſolution of coming home to his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as he intended to do, at any rate, he ſhould loſe the Kings Favour, which he had ſo lately procured; therefore he reſolved to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his mind, as Courteouſly as was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo as not to give the King any ground to hope that he ſhould tarry; ſo obſerving that the King by his ſtedfaſt looking in his Face, expected a preſent anſwer, he addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him in theſe terms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt Mighty King, I muſt acknowledge
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59471:78"/> that there is more than words required in a man of my Character, to retaliate ſo great and ſignal Honours, as your Majeſty hath ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to me, ever ſince I had the happineſs to ſee your face; ſo that now I am forced to acknowledg my ſelf unhappy in that I want opportunity to expreſs the ſame. As to what your Majeſty requires of me; I heartily wiſh it were in my Power to comply with your Demand, but it is now paſt help; for I have put my ſelf under an inevitable neceſſity, of begging your Majeſties Pardon in that Point. I have been for many years abſent from my Native Country, and have put on a reſolution, and put my ſelf under a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to return with the firſt occaſion; ſo that now my hands are tyed up, that I cannot obey your Majeſties Demand in this point, for which I am heartily ſorry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King finding him thus peremptory, reſolved to expreſs a great deal of Grief, but no diſpleaſure at him; he told him, ſince it was ſo, he expected that he would not be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in his departure: to which the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and tarryed ſeveral days; but at laſt took leave of the King, and all his Court, and was diſmiſſed with all the expreſſions of Honour imaginable. But theſe Knights, who upon the Death of the Gyant, had made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, reſolved to convey him a
<pb facs="tcp:59471:78"/> part of his way, which accordingly they did. Their way from the Royal City, lay through the Wood, where the Gyant reſided; and from thence he advanced to the Fatal Conflict with our Champion. The Wood, although fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently paſſed through in former times, yet for a great while before this, it became a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Wilderneſs, by reaſon of the Savage Creatures poſſeſſing it, which made people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to come nigh it; the common Road alſo was ſo overgrown with Buſhes and Shrubs, that there was hardly any appearance of it to be ſeen: yet notwithſtanding, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> being deſirous to ſee his late Antagoniſt's Habitation, and to know them, he left to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him, if they were diſpoſed to revenge his Quarrel; the other Knights alſo willing to ſatisfy their Curioſity, and that they might brag afterwards that they were among the firſt that entered the deſolate Forreſt, after the Death of the Monſter; all conclude V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly to take their way through the Wood, reſolving they ſhould make ſome ſearch, as they paſſed along the Monſters Mannor.</p>
               <p>Thus they entered the Wood, about Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon, having left all the Servants without the Wood, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to return home; only St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> becauſe he was not to return again that way, took <hi>Mack</hi> along with him. They were not
<pb facs="tcp:59471:79"/> half an hour in the Wood, when they began to queſtion where they were; the Knights proteſted, that though they have many times paſſed through, yet now they knew not where they were; and that which bewilders me moſt (ſays one of them) is, that I ſee a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain yonder, over againſt me, which ſo far as I can remember, was not to be ſeen here in former times; to which all the reſt of the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Knights agreed, ſaying, That unqueſtionably, this muſt be ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Thing: Whereupon, they all Rode to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, to ſee it; But when they drew near it, they could diſcern it was an Houſe built with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Stone, and Wood, and ſuch Materials as the Place could afford, to a prodigious Bigneſs: when they came to the door, they began to adviſe, whether it was ſafe to go in: But St. <hi>Patrick</hi> was ſo bent for it, that he made them preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntly co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nt: So they entered, every man having his Sword drawn, expecting to meet with ſome rugged fellows; but they were much miſtaken, for they found none there, except an Old Man of about an Hundred years of Age, who ſate by the Fire very Penſive; to him St. <hi>Patrick</hi> Addreſſed himſelf, in theſe terms. <hi>How now Old Man, What is become of the reſt of your Company?</hi> to him the Old man anſwers ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſurly, You may go look; Nay, ſays the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:59471:79"/> other, <hi>I am not come hither to offend you; yet I think, I may ſafely ask you this queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is commonly the firſt that is asked of a Solitary man, by ſuch as Viſit him:</hi> Then the Old man became a little more calm, and told them how that his Son was Killed ſome days ago in a Duel, hard by the King of <hi>Sicilies</hi> Houſe, and now his other Sons, and the reſt of his Friends were gone to bury him; but he would not tell them where, nor were they very curious to enquire: ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving viewed the Houſe, both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, the Old man directed them out of the Wood, where they heartily, and ſorrowfully did bid adieu to each other.</p>
               <p>Our Champion having for many years raiſed Piramids to his memory, both here, and in all the parts of Greece: Where he fought ſuch Battels, and did ſuch Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exploits; that his Name began to out-ſound that of his own Trojan Hector. At length he embraced a firm reſolution to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into his own Native Country; which he did, and having long confined himſelf to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired Life, at length gave up his great Soul to the Conqueror of all Champions, Death.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Patrick,</hi> the Worlds-wonder, when his Sword</l>
                  <l>O're Witches, Gyants, had proclaim'd him Lord;</l>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:59471:80"/>
                  <l>When by his hand, the Mightieſt Monſters fell:</l>
                  <l>And Seas, and Shoars, his unmatcht Wonders tell:</l>
                  <l>After Proud <hi>Greece,</hi> rais'd Temples to his Name,</l>
                  <l>And the whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe Proclaim'd his Fame;</l>
                  <l>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, a Theatre too ſcant,</l>
                  <l>His Numberleſs Heroick Arts to Paint!</l>
                  <l>Calmly unto his Native Soil retires,</l>
                  <l>And there doth Expiate his Martial Fires.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ireland,</hi> to Thee <hi>Patrick,</hi> this Honour gave,</l>
                  <l>To be thy Patron, who gav'ſt him a Grave:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Mighty <hi>Monarchs</hi> to his Tomb do bring,</l>
                  <l>Their great Encomiums, &amp; Wiſe Bards do Sing</l>
                  <l>His Valours Praiſe, of which the world doth ring.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59471:80"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
